<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Stories for Earth</title>
	<atom:link href="/tag/kim-stanley-robinson/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Stories for Earth is a climate change podcast that critically engages with stories that can teach us strength and resilience in fighting the climate crisis.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 23 Dec 2024 15:53:37 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.7.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>&#8220;New York 2140&#8221; by Kim Stanley Robinson: Summary &#038; Analysis</title>
		<link>/2022/01/03/new-york-2140-kim-stanley-robinson/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Forrest Brown]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 03 Jan 2022 19:41:14 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Episodes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[books]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[kim stanley robinson]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[season 3]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://storiesforearth.com/?p=1704</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>New York 2140 is the story of how a future New York City adapts to climate change and works to build a better world.</p>
<p>The post <a href="/2022/01/03/new-york-2140-kim-stanley-robinson/">&#8220;New York 2140&#8221; by Kim Stanley Robinson: Summary &amp; Analysis</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Stories for Earth</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><em>Stories for Earth relies on contributions from our listeners and readers to produce high quality, in-depth content. If you buy something using the links on our website, we may</em> <em>earn a small commission, at no extra cost to you. <em>For more information</em>, see our <a href="https://storiesforearth.com/affiliate-disclosure/">Affiliate Disclosure</a>.</em></p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator" />



<p>Widely regarded as a masterpiece of climate fiction and solarpunk, <em>New York 2140</em> by Kim Stanley Robinson is a sprawling novel about how New York City has adapted to climate chaos in the 22nd century. In this special two-part episode, I&#8217;ll first offer a plot summary and list of characters, followed by analysis of major themes. This is a long book with a lot to teach us about what a better world could look like and how we might get there, so I&#8217;m excited to finally discuss it on the podcast!</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-rich is-provider-spotify wp-block-embed-spotify wp-embed-aspect-21-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="embed-spotify"><iframe title="Spotify Embed: S3 E3.0 &quot;New York 2140&quot; by Kim Stanley Robinson" style="border-radius: 12px" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/episode/2kgK4jaNGLMQkRnWCaIMQd?si=6f22659664544d38&#038;utm_source=oembed"></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-medium"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="257" height="400" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/new-york-2140-cover.jpeg?w=193" alt="The book cover for New York 2140 by Kim Stanley Robinson." class="wp-image-1707" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/new-york-2140-cover.jpeg 257w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/01/new-york-2140-cover-193x300.jpeg 193w" sizes="(max-width: 257px) 100vw, 257px" /></figure>



<p>→ <a href="https://www.betterworldbooks.com/product/detail/New-York-2140-9780316262316" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Buy <strong>USED</strong> on Better World Books from $7.48</a><br>→ <a href="https://bookshop.org/a/140/9780316262316">Buy <strong>NEW</strong> on Bookshop from $16.55</a> (affiliate)<br>→ <a href="http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/993559833" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Find at your local library</a></p>



<div class="wp-block-cover alignfull has-background-dim has-background-gradient" style="background:linear-gradient(135deg,rgb(92,145,60) 0%,rgb(169,209,153) 100%);min-height:350px;aspect-ratio:unset;"><div class="wp-block-cover__inner-container is-layout-flow wp-block-cover-is-layout-flow">
<div class="wp-block-jetpack-layout-grid alignfull column1-desktop-grid__span-10 column1-desktop-grid__start-2 column1-desktop-grid__row-1 column1-tablet-grid__span-8 column1-tablet-grid__row-1 column1-mobile-grid__span-4 column1-mobile-grid__row-1 wp-block-jetpack-layout-gutter__medium">
<div class="wp-block-jetpack-layout-grid-column wp-block-jetpack-layout-grid__padding-none">
<h3 class="has-text-color wp-block-heading" style="color:#ffffff;font-size:clamp(30.693px, 1.918rem + ((1vw - 3.2px) * 2.285), 54px);px;">Never miss an episode</h3>



<p class="margin-bottom-half has-text-color" style="color:#ffffff;font-size:clamp(14px, 0.875rem + ((1vw - 3.2px) * 0.392), 18px);px;">Subscribe wherever you enjoy podcasts:</p>



<div class="wp-block-buttons margin-top-none is-layout-flex wp-block-buttons-is-layout-flex">
<div class="wp-block-button is-style-outline is-style-outline--1"><a class="wp-block-button__link has-text-color" href="https://podcasts.apple.com/us/podcast/stories-for-earth-with-forrest-brown/id1478061144" style="color:#ffffff;" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Apple</a></div>



<div class="wp-block-button is-style-outline is-style-outline--2"><a class="wp-block-button__link has-text-color" href="https://open.spotify.com/show/1p08YiP5SoxJEoFJyeebxR" style="color:#ffffff;" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Spotify</a></div>



<div class="wp-block-button is-style-outline is-style-outline--3"><a class="wp-block-button__link has-text-color" href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCGmH6FisTges9AzQlfbg-hg" style="color:#ffffff;" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">YouTube</a></div>



<div class="wp-block-button is-style-outline is-style-outline--4"><a class="wp-block-button__link has-text-color" href="https://www.stitcher.com/s?fid=463345&amp;refid=stpr" style="color:#ffffff;" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Stitcher</a></div>



<div class="wp-block-button is-style-outline is-style-outline--5"><a class="wp-block-button__link has-text-color" href="https://anchor.fm/s/113fd96c/podcast/rss" style="color:#ffffff;" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">RSS</a></div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div></div>



<hr class="wp-block-separator" />



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="top">Jump to</h2>



<ol class="wp-block-list"><li><a href="#about">About Kim Stanley Robinson</a></li><li><a href="#transcript">Transcript</a><ol><li><a href="#introduction-to-new-york-2140">Introduction to &#8220;New York 2140&#8221;</a></li><li><a href="#summary-of-new-york-2140">Summary of &#8220;New York 2140&#8221;</a><ol><li><a href="#setting">Setting</a></li><li><a href="#character-list">Character list</a></li><li><a href="#plot-summary">Plot summary</a></li></ol></li><li><a href="#outro">Outro</a></li></ol></li><li><a href="#recommendations">Recommendations</a></li></ol>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="about">About the creator</h2>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-medium"><img decoding="async" width="460" height="480" src="/wp-content/uploads/2020/02/460px-kim_stanley_robinson_by_gage_skidmore_2.jpg?w=288" alt="" class="wp-image-720" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2020/02/460px-kim_stanley_robinson_by_gage_skidmore_2.jpg 460w, /wp-content/uploads/2020/02/460px-kim_stanley_robinson_by_gage_skidmore_2-288x300.jpg 288w" sizes="(max-width: 460px) 100vw, 460px" /><figcaption>By Gage Skidmore, CC BY-SA 3.0,&nbsp;<a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/w/index.php?curid=72961714" target="_blank">https://commons.wikimedia.org/w/index.php?curid=72961714</a></figcaption></figure>



<p>Kim Stanley Robinson is a literary science fiction writer from Davis, California. Born in Waukegan, Illinois in 1952, Robinson moved to Southern California as a child but has also lived in Washington, D.C. and Switzerland. His books frequently incorporate themes of climate change, sustainability, nature, environmental justice, and critiques of capitalism. The author of over 19 books and numerous short stories, Robinson has been awarded the&nbsp;<a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="http://www.thehugoawards.org/" target="_blank">Hugo</a>,&nbsp;<a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://nebulas.sfwa.org/" target="_blank">Nebula</a>, and&nbsp;<a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://clarkeaward.com/" target="_blank">Arthur C. Clarke Awards</a>&nbsp;for his literary contributions to science fiction. He holds a BA in literature from UC San Diego, an MA in English from Boston University, and a PhD in English from UC San Diego, and he has taught at UC Davis and the&nbsp;<a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="http://clarion.ucsd.edu/" target="_blank">Clarion Science Fiction and Fantasy Writers’ Workshop</a>. His latest novel,&nbsp;<em>The Ministry for the Future,</em>&nbsp;was published in fall 2020.</p>



<p><strong>Official website:</strong>&nbsp;<a href="https://www.kimstanleyrobinson.info/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">https://www.kimstanleyrobinson.info/</a></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="transcript">Transcript</h2>



<p><a href="#top">Back to top ↑</a></p>



<p>I’m Forrest Brown, and you’re listening to <em>Stories for Earth</em>.</p>



<p><em>[music: “Cold Descent” by Forrest Brown]</em></p>



<p>You’re listening to Stories for Earth, a podcast about everything climate change in pop culture.</p>



<p>Today, we’re talking about Kim Stanley Robinson’s novel <em>New York 2140</em>. It’s a long one, so we’re covering it in two parts. You’re listening to part one, where we’ll provide a plot summary of the book. Part two will cover a discussion of major themes and will be available a few weeks after the release of part one.</p>



<p>If you’d like to support further production of the show, consider becoming a member on Patreon for as little as $1 per month. We’re on Twitter and Instagram, and our website is storiesforearth.com.</p>



<p>And now, here’s part one of our discussion of <em>New York 2140</em>. I hope you enjoy.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="introduction-to-new-york-2140">Introduction to &#8220;New York 2140&#8221;</h3>



<p><a href="#top">Back to top ↑</a></p>



<p><em>&#8220;The proletarian movement is the self-conscious, independent movement of the immense majority in the interest of the immense majority.&#8221; -Karl Marx and Friedrich Engels, </em>The Communist Manifesto</p>



<p><em>&#8220;Ecology without class struggle is gardening.&#8221; -Chico Mendes, Brazilian trade union leader and environmentalist</em></p>



<p>During the first year of the COVID-19 pandemic, the world’s 2,365 billionaires became $4 trillion—or 54 percent—richer, according to a March 2021 <a href="https://inequality.org/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/Report-GlobalBillionaires-March31-2021.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">analysis</a> from the Program on Inequality at the Institute for Policy Studies (IPS). While the pandemic has killed <a href="https://covid19.who.int/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">millions of people</a> around the world and <a href="https://www.cbsnews.com/news/oxfam-billionaire-wealth-poverty/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">doubled</a> the global poverty rate, it’s been kind to the world’s richest people, further widening the already gaping wealth disparity between the haves and the have-nots.</p>



<p>This should come as no surprise if you’re familiar with Naomi Klein’s 2007 book <em>The</em> <em>Shock Doctrine: The Rise of Disaster Capitalism</em>. <em>The Shock Doctrine</em> examines how capitalism has taken advantage of and benefitted from moments of crisis, subverting the popular narrative of free market capitalism’s peaceful triumph over the 20th century. From the collapse of the Soviet Union to the rise of the fascist dictator Augusto Pinochet in Chile to the 2003 US invasion of Iraq, Klein demonstrates how capitalism pounces on moments of social upheaval and extreme violence to create economic opportunity.</p>



<p><strong>Also read:</strong> <a href="https://storiesforearth.com/2020/02/25/pacific-edge-kim-stanley-robinson/">&#8220;Pacific Edge&#8221; by Kim Stanley Robinson: A Future Mythology</a></p>



<p>We’re seeing the Shock Doctrine at play in real time with the COVID-19 pandemic, and many people, myself included, believe we’ll see it again and again as extreme weather events made worse by climate change become more frequent. Given shifting messaging from capitalists and neoliberal politicians, you might say it’s already happening.</p>



<p>Take, for example, recent remarks made by venture capitalist John Doerr, in which he called climate change the “…largest economic opportunity of the 21st Century,” according to <a href="https://www.marketwatch.com/story/vc-legend-john-doerr-says-climate-change-brings-economic-opportunity-thats-bigger-than-the-internet-boom-11636466626" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><em>MarketWatch</em></a>. You can also see this in the way shipping companies are <a href="https://maritime-executive.com/article/melting-ice-caps-and-new-shipping-lanes" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">gushing</a> about melting Arctic ice opening up new shipping lanes for trade. Or for a more lengthy analysis, consider the 2014 book <em>Windfall: The Booming Business of Global Warming</em> by Mckenzie Funk.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="summary-of-new-york-2140">Summary of “New York 2140”</h2>



<p><a href="#top">Back to top ↑</a></p>



<p>But it’s not just captains of industry and heads of state who hear <em>cha-ching</em> when they think of climate change. Science fiction writer Kim Stanley Robinson has seen the writing on the wall for the next big money making crisis, writing his 2017 novel <em>New York 2140</em> about this very phenomenon and exploring a possible solution for escaping it.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="setting">Setting</h3>



<p><a href="#top">Back to top ↑</a></p>



<p>Set over a century in the future, <em>New York 2140</em> takes place after some of the most cataclysmic effects of climate change have been felt. Based on the extremely high sea level rise seen in the novel, it’s safe to assume the world has blown past the Paris Agreement target to limit global warming to 1.5ºC above the pre-industrial average. Much of Lower Manhattan is now partially submerged, with neighboring boroughs like Brooklyn almost totally drowned. The ultra-wealthy live Uptown in superscrapers—dizzyingly tall skyscrapers—and Wall Street is fleeing for higher ground in Denver, Colorado.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" width="512" height="205" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/512px-lower_manhattan_from_jersey_city_november_2014_panorama_2.jpeg?w=512" alt="A photo of the Lower Manhattan skyline as seen from New Jersey in 2014." class="wp-image-1725" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/512px-lower_manhattan_from_jersey_city_november_2014_panorama_2.jpeg 512w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/01/512px-lower_manhattan_from_jersey_city_november_2014_panorama_2-300x120.jpeg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 512px) 100vw, 512px" /><figcaption><a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Lower_Manhattan_from_Jersey_City_November_2014_panorama_2.jpg" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">King of Hearts / Wikimedia Commons / CC-BY-SA-3.0</a>, <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">CC BY-SA 3.0</a>, via Wikimedia Commons</figcaption></figure>



<p>Lower Manhattan is now known as “the intertidal,” where flooded roads have transformed into canals and skyscrapers have been converted into partially self-sustaining housing co-ops for the dwindling middle class. Those not fortunate enough to make it into one of these vertical villages survive by squatting in the crumbling ruins of shorter buildings, which now serve as poker chips for investors in a kind of climate-induced housing bubble.</p>



<p>Being a New York novel, finance plays a big role in this story, and it can be easy to feel lost at times if you don’t have a basic understanding of finance or economics. But more than anything, <em>New York 2140</em> is a massive exercise in worldbuilding, where Kim Stanley Robinson has seemingly imagined every conceivable aspect of a future New York and chosen to follow the lives of ten main characters over the course of about three years. While most of the characters are neighbors living quite different lives as residents of the Met Life Tower, four of them are lumped into pairs and another one represents the city itself as a character.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="character-list">Character list</h3>



<p><a href="#top">Back to top ↑</a></p>



<p>To briefly summarize, the characters are as follows:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list"><li><strong>Mutt and Jeff—</strong>two unemployed financial analysts living in a hotello (a sort of pop-up tent) in the vertical farm of the Met Life Tower</li><li><strong>Inspector Gen—</strong>an NYPD investigator who works on cracking a series of mysterious and seemingly unrelated cases throughout the novel</li><li><strong>Franklin Garr—</strong>a cocky young hedge fund trader who becomes the mastermind behind the largest debt strike in history</li><li><strong>Vlade—</strong>a middle-aged Ukrainian immigrant who works as the superintendent of the Met Life Tower</li><li><strong>The Citizen—</strong>a somewhat Shakespearean character who embodies the voice of New York City, often providing helpful historical context and snarky comedic relief in what I can only hear as a classic Manhattan accent</li><li><strong>Amelia Black—</strong>a futuristic streamer of sorts who hosts an internet show where she rescues endangered species and moves them to more hospitable environments as the climate continues to make ecosystems shapeshift</li><li><strong>Charlotte Armstrong—</strong>the chairperson of the Met Life Tower housing cooperative who works for the Householders’ Union, an NGO working to help those in need secure housing</li><li><strong>Stefan and Roberto—</strong>two “water rat” young boys orphaned in the intertidal who have had to learn to fend for themselves and are obsessed with hunting for buried treasure</li></ul>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="plot-summary">Plot summary</h3>



<p><a href="#top">Back to top ↑</a></p>



<p><em>New York 2140 </em>is a sweeping novel that contains many subplots, but the overarching plot has to do with changing the global financial system for the good and transitioning to a post-capitalist economic system. Simple topics, I know. Stay with me.</p>



<p>The book starts with a sort of socialist realist version of a Statler and Waldorf skit from <em>The Muppet Show</em>. Jeff is lecturing Mutt on the problems with capitalism and how he has a plan to make tiny tweaks to what he has identified as the 16 financial laws that govern the global financial system. Thanks to computer access granted by a recent freelance project for Jeff’s cousin who works in finance, Jeff can actually deploy the code he’s written to change these laws and hopefully save the world from greed and exploitation in the process.</p>



<p>Except, right after Jeff pushes the code revisions, the two realize they’ve been caught and have to make a run for it. The men go missing, and Charlotte Armstrong—chairperson of the Met Life tower housing co-op—files a police report. While Inspector Gen gets started on the case, a peppy and opportunistic Franklin Garr boats to work at WaterPrice, a hedge fund firm that manages investments in sea level and housing securities.</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center" style="font-size:28px;"><strong>Has this info helped you?</strong></p>



<p class="has-text-align-center has-normal-font-size"><em>Stories for Earth is and always will be a free resource to help people imagine brighter futures through the material we discuss. It&#8217;s also created and paid for by one person! Apart from occasional affiliate revenue, donations from people like you is the only way Stories for Earth remains financially feasible.</em></p>



<div class="wp-block-button aligncenter"><a class="wp-block-button__link has-very-light-gray-color has-luminous-vivid-orange-background-color has-text-color has-background" href="https://www.patreon.com/storiesforearth" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Support on Patreon</a></div>



<p></p>



<div class="wp-block-buttons is-content-justification-center is-layout-flex wp-container-core-buttons-is-layout-2 wp-block-buttons-is-layout-flex">
<div class="wp-block-button is-style-fill"><a class="wp-block-button__link has-vivid-cyan-blue-background-color has-background" href="https://venmo.com/code?user_id=3241757261168640196" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Donate on Venmo</a></div>
</div>



<p>Franklin is somewhat of a wunderkind at WaterPrice thanks to his invention of something called the Intertidal Property Pricing Index, or the IPPI. This is where the book starts to lose some people since it can get a little technical with finance-talk, so I’ll do my best to explain it here.</p>



<p>In 2140, sea level rise is tracked religiously, thanks to the traumas of the past one-hundred-plus years when sea levels rose dramatically and rapidly, mostly in two events called the First and Second Pulse. These were episodes of massive sea level rise in a very short amount of time due to major collapses in the Antarctic and Greenland ice sheets. Both Pulses caused incalculable amounts of destruction to coastal communities around the world, and everyone is paranoid about the prospect of a Third Pulse happening.</p>



<p>True to form, Wall Street and other financial hubs found a way to make betting on sea level rise a lucrative business. Now, sea level has its own index on the stock market, just like the top 500 publicly traded companies have the S&amp;P 500 today. Housing has its own index as well. So, to put it simply, this index that Franklin Garr has created—the Intertidal Property Pricing Index—functions to produce an accurate, real-time price estimate of coastal property based on the global rise and fall of sea level.</p>



<p><strong>Also read:</strong> <a href="https://storiesforearth.com/2020/01/14/ishmael-daniel-quinn-climate-change/">&#8220;Ishmael&#8221; by Daniel Quinn, Climate Change, and Moving Beyond a Vision of Doom</a></p>



<p>This helps to explain why buildings in the intertidal zone of New York City are so valuable now. Even though the East Coast is largely drowned, people haven’t totally abandoned their homes, stubbornly sticking around through some drastic adaptation measures. The submerged ground floors of buildings are totally sealed off to prevent flooding, and buildings have been reinforced with <a href="https://www.digitaltrends.com/cool-tech/what-is-graphene/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">graphene</a> to keep them from tumbling into the polluted water.</p>



<p>However, this interest in betting on housing prices has led to a fiercely competitive housing market, which is causing some stress for Charlotte Armstrong. The Met Life tower housing co-op has recently learned of a bid from an unknown party to buy the building, and the size of the bid smells like an attempt at a hostile takeover. Forced to put the bid to a vote among the tower’s residents, the co-op narrowly avoids getting bought out, but Charlotte is rattled by this and determined to find out who’s behind the bid.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="512" height="683" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/512px-metropolitan_life_insurance_co_bldg_01.jpeg?w=225" alt="A photo of the Metropolitan Life Insurance building in New York City from 2008." class="wp-image-1723" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/512px-metropolitan_life_insurance_co_bldg_01.jpeg 512w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/01/512px-metropolitan_life_insurance_co_bldg_01-225x300.jpeg 225w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 512px) 100vw, 512px" /><figcaption><a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Metropolitan_Life_Insurance_Co_Bldg_01.jpg" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Gigi alt</a>, <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">CC BY-SA 3.0</a>, via Wikimedia Commons</figcaption></figure>



<p>To complicate things, it seems someone is trying to sabotage the Met Life tower. Vlade, the building’s superintendent, gets an alert early one morning of a leak in the building’s basement. Upon inspection, it appears someone has intentionally drilled through one of the walls facing the outside canal. Vlade manages to contain and patch the leak, but the event is still unsettling. Charlotte suspects whoever tried to buy the Met Life tower might be behind it.</p>



<p>Meanwhile, we’re introduced to Amelia Black, a “cloud” star who hosts a popular show called <em>Assisted Migration</em>, named after the giant airship she flies of the same name. Amelia is on a mission to relocate some starving polar bears to Antarctica, where conditions are still similar enough to their ideal environment to give them a chance at survival. Stefan and Roberto—two orphaned young boys who live in the canals—make an appearance after Franklin Garr saves them from drowning. Vlade takes them under his wing, and they eventually spill the beans about their plans to salvage the wreckage of an old British ship they’ve found and hopefully recover some sunken treasure.</p>



<p>Vlade goes on a couple of other treasure hunts with the boys, eventually employing the help of his ex-wife Idelba and her boat to recover the gold from the wreckage of the <em>HMS Hussar</em>. It’s on one of these expeditions that Vlade accidentally finds Mutt and Jeff, who have been held prisoner in a kind of underwater facility on the bottom of the bay. This gives Inspector Gen some new leads, who eventually narrows the list of suspects down to Jeff’s cousin, a hedge fund manager named Henry Vinson.</p>



<p>Seemingly unbeknownst to him, Vinson’s hedge fund, Albany Albany, hired a private security firm to kidnap Mutt and Jeff, though we later find out it was Charlotte’s ex-husband and chair of the Federal Reserve who ordered the kidnapping under the guise of placing them in witness protection. Mutt and Jeff’s rescue also provides some evidence that Vinson’s hedge fund was going through Morningside Realty in the attempted buy-out of the Met Life tower.</p>



<p>These discoveries are soon overshadowed by news that a massive hurricane is heading for New York City, and the residents of the Met Life tower scramble to prepare for what is likely to be a nasty storm. Amelia Black is forced to delay her return home, flying north to ride out the storm, and Stefan and Roberto go missing after they’re caught in the storm while trying to find the grave of Herman Melville, the author of <em>Moby Dick</em>.</p>



<p>The other main characters hunker down in the Met Life tower, which emerges relatively unscathed compared to some of the other nearby buildings. However, the intertidal zone where the poor live as squatters in crumbling buildings, is completely annihilated, and Vlade and his ex-wife Idelba venture out in her tugboat to save as many people as possible from the lethal storm surge.</p>



<p>In the aftermath of the hurricane, hundreds of people have perished, and thousands more are effectively climate refugees—now homeless and living in a massive open-air refugee camp in the wreckage of Central Park. Charlotte is overwhelmed with requests to the Householder’s Union, and she makes an unsuccessful attempt to convince the mayor to seize all the unused housing uptown that has been bought up by rich investors. A riot ensues after the refugees are essentially abandoned by the city, and the NYPD gets locked into a tense standoff with the same private security company who kidnapped Mutt and Jeff.</p>



<p>Inspector Gen manages to de-escalate the situation, but not without getting some important information on who the security company works for—Henry Vinson. By this point, Vinson’s name has been found to be connected to a number of mysteries throughout the novel, from the hostile buyout of the Met Life tower to Mutt and Jeff’s kidnapping to a private security firm threatening to shoot rioters attempting to breach a pretty much vacant building.</p>



<p>This eventually gets back to the hedge fund trader, Franklin Garr. Remembering a conversation he’d previously had with Charlotte Armstrong about how a debt strike could bring the global financial system to its knees to better serve everyday people, Franklin springs into action. He calls up Charlotte, and the two hatch a plan to make the debt strike a reality. Amelia Black also gets in on the action, using her enormous platform as a cloud star to send the rallying cry.</p>



<p>What is this debt strike? It’s basically an intentional recreation of the 2008 financial crisis. If you recall, the 2008 financial crisis happened because a housing bubble collapsed in the United States. This caused a domino effect of economic consequences that resulted in the global Great Recession.</p>



<p>In very simple terms, banks approved a lot of predatory mortgages to people who most likely could not afford them. And by that I mean they started issuing mortgages like what they called “No Income, No Assets” or Ninja loans. When these people inevitably couldn’t make payments on their mortgages anymore, thousands of houses went into foreclosure, and behemoth investment banks like Bear Stearns went bankrupt. If you want a really entertaining and accessible explanation of what happened, I highly recommend the movie <em>The Big Short</em>.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="embed-youtube"><iframe loading="lazy" title="The Big Short Trailer (2015) ‐ Paramount Pictures" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/vgqG3ITMv1Q?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p>This is essentially the kind of financial crisis Franklin, Charlotte, and Amelia helped orchestrate. Except this time, mortgage payments stopped because hundreds of thousands of people made a choice to stop paying them all at the same time rather than being forced to stop making payments out of financial necessity. Just as they hoped, this caused a domino effect that brought the global financial system down. The banks asked for a government bailout, but this time was different from the series of stimulus packages Congress passed in 2009.</p>



<p>Governments around the world still bailed out financial institutions but in exchange for nationalization. In other words, governments gave them the cash they needed to survive on the condition that the money go towards buying shares. This effectively made governments around the world majority shareholders in the various failing financial institutions, thereby netting them a lot of revenue for their national budgets.</p>



<p>What happens next is a bit of a blur. With bolstered confidence from the successful nationalization of Wall Street, Congress passed a flurry of legislation straight from a progressive Democrat’s wildest dreams: universal healthcare, free college tuition, full employment, programs, aggressive environmental protections, a corporate tax rate of 90 percent, laws preventing capital flight to tax havens, et cetera.</p>



<p>Thus ends <em>New York 2140</em>. It’s a long and wild ride with lots to say about the fundamental brokenness of our current neoliberal era marked by extreme wealth inequality, climate breakdown, fascism, and disaster capitalism. And yet, despite a tendency to pontificate and perhaps lean too heavily on historical events from the early 21st century, it’s a pleasant and engaging read that has a lot to teach us about human resiliency and the power of collective action.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="outro">Outro</h3>



<p><a href="#top">Back to top ↑</a></p>



<p>I’m doing this episode a bit differently from past ones, so be on the lookout for part two of our episode on <em>New York 2140</em>, where we’ll move beyond a plot summary to analyze some of the major themes in the novel.</p>



<p>In the meantime, be sure to follow us on Twitter and Instagram, and check out our website at storiesforearth.com. If you’d like to support further production of the show, consider becoming a member on Patreon for as little as $1 per month.</p>



<p>Thanks for listening, and I’ll talk to you soon.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="recommendations">Recommendations</h2>



<p><a href="#top">Back to top ↑</a></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="255" height="400" src="/wp-content/uploads/2020/02/pacific-edge-book-cover.jpg?w=191" alt="" class="wp-image-712" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2020/02/pacific-edge-book-cover.jpg 255w, /wp-content/uploads/2020/02/pacific-edge-book-cover-191x300.jpg 191w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 255px) 100vw, 255px" /></figure>



<p><strong>Book:</strong> <em>Pacific Edge</em> by Kim Stanley Robinson</p>



<p>→ <a href="https://www.betterworldbooks.com/product/detail/Pacific-Edge---Three-Californias-9780312890384" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Buy <strong>USED</strong> on Better World Books from $5.44</a><br>→ <a href="https://bookshop.org/a/140/9780312890384" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Buy <strong>NEW</strong> on Bookshop from $22.07</a> (affiliate)<br>→ <a href="http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/1023125245" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Find at your local library</a></p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator" />



<figure class="wp-block-image size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="267" height="400" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/the-shock-doctrine-by-naomi-klein.jpeg?w=200" alt="Book cover for The Shock Doctrine by Naomi Klein." class="wp-image-1563" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/the-shock-doctrine-by-naomi-klein.jpeg 267w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/08/the-shock-doctrine-by-naomi-klein-200x300.jpeg 200w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 267px) 100vw, 267px" /></figure>



<p><strong>Book:</strong> <em>The Shock Doctrine: The Rise of Disaster Capitalism</em> by Naomi Klein</p>



<p>→ <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.betterworldbooks.com/product/detail/Shock-Doctrine---The-Rise-of-Disaster-Capitalism-9780312427993" target="_blank">Buy <strong>USED</strong> on Better World Books from $5.05</a> <br>→ <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://bookshop.org/a/140/9780312427993" target="_blank">Buy <strong>NEW</strong> on Bookshop from $20.24</a> (affiliate)<br>→ <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/1003865219" target="_blank">Find at your local library</a></p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator" />



<figure class="wp-block-image size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="267" height="400" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/sunvault-book-cover.jpeg?w=200" alt="Book cover for Sunvault: Stories of Solarpunk and Eco-Speculation." class="wp-image-1718" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/sunvault-book-cover.jpeg 267w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/01/sunvault-book-cover-200x300.jpeg 200w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 267px) 100vw, 267px" /></figure>



<p><strong>Book:</strong> <em>Sunvault: Stories of Solarpunk and Eco-Speculation</em> edited by Phoebe Wagner and Brontë Christopher Wieland</p>



<p>→ <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://bookshop.org/a/140/9781937794750" target="_blank">Buy <strong>NEW</strong> on Bookshop from $12.87</a> (affiliate)<br>→ <a href="http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/1001569674" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Find at your local library</a></p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator" />



<p><strong>Article:</strong> &#8220;<a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://hieroglyph.asu.edu/2014/09/solarpunk-notes-toward-a-manifesto/" target="_blank">Solarpunk: Notes toward a manifesto</a>&#8221; by Adam Flynn in <em>Hieroglyph</em></p>



<div class="wp-block-group alignfull"><div class="wp-block-group__inner-container is-layout-flow wp-block-group-is-layout-flow">
<div class="wp-block-coblocks-hero alignfull coblocks-hero-82610395659"><div class="wp-block-coblocks-hero__inner has-background hero-center-left-align has-padding has-huge-padding has-left-content" style="background-color:#f3f3f3;min-height:500px;"><div class="wp-block-coblocks-hero__content-wrapper"><div class="wp-block-coblocks-hero__content" style="max-width:560px;">
<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Like what you see? Become a Patreon member today for as little as $1 a month.</h2>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.patreon.com/storiesforearth" target="_blank"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="434" height="102" src="/wp-content/uploads/2020/12/become_a_patron_button402x.png?w=434" alt="" class="wp-image-1007" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2020/12/become_a_patron_button402x.png 434w, /wp-content/uploads/2020/12/become_a_patron_button402x-300x71.png 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 434px) 100vw, 434px" /></a></figure>
</div></div></div></div>
</div></div>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="/2022/01/03/new-york-2140-kim-stanley-robinson/">&#8220;New York 2140&#8221; by Kim Stanley Robinson: Summary &amp; Analysis</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Stories for Earth</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>&#8220;Pacific Edge&#8221; by Kim Stanley Robinson: A Future Mythology</title>
		<link>/2020/02/25/pacific-edge-kim-stanley-robinson/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Forrest Brown]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2020 12:00:41 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Episodes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Start Here]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[books]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[climate change]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[kim stanley robinson]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://storiesforearth.com/?p=710</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Our discussion of Pacific Edge by Kim Stanley Robinson covers a plot summary and explores what our future can look like through this utopian eco fiction novel.</p>
<p>The post <a href="/2020/02/25/pacific-edge-kim-stanley-robinson/">&#8220;Pacific Edge&#8221; by Kim Stanley Robinson: A Future Mythology</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Stories for Earth</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><em>Stories for Earth relies on contributions from our listeners and readers to produce high quality, in-depth content. If you buy something using the links on our website, we may</em> <em>earn a small commission, at no extra cost to you. <em>For more information</em>, see our <a href="https://storiesforearth.com/affiliate-disclosure/">Affiliate Disclosure</a>.</em></p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator" />



<p>Kim Stanley Robinson&#8217;s 1990 classic <em>Pacific Edge</em> is an inspiring vision of how we might create a truly sustainable society. Part of a three part series—or triptych—the novel presents a utopian or solarpunk imagining of Orange County, California in the 2060s, telling the story of Kevin Claiborne as he and his friends attempt to stop an ecologically destructive zoning proposal on one of the last pristine hillsides in their neighborhood of El Modena.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-rich is-provider-spotify wp-block-embed-spotify wp-embed-aspect-21-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="embed-spotify"><iframe title="Spotify Embed: S1 E6: Pacific Edge by Kim Stanley Robinson: A Future Mythology" style="border-radius: 12px" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/episode/3oX8I1EuwHwQQswBIfmpl1?utm_source=oembed"></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<div class="wp-block-cover alignfull has-background-dim has-background-gradient" style="background:linear-gradient(135deg,rgb(92,145,60) 0%,rgb(169,209,153) 100%);min-height:350px;aspect-ratio:unset;"><div class="wp-block-cover__inner-container is-layout-flow wp-block-cover-is-layout-flow">
<div class="wp-block-jetpack-layout-grid alignfull column1-desktop-grid__span-10 column1-desktop-grid__start-2 column1-desktop-grid__row-1 column1-tablet-grid__span-8 column1-tablet-grid__row-1 column1-mobile-grid__span-4 column1-mobile-grid__row-1 wp-block-jetpack-layout-gutter__medium">
<div class="wp-block-jetpack-layout-grid-column wp-block-jetpack-layout-grid__padding-none">
<h3 class="has-text-color wp-block-heading" style="color:#ffffff;font-size:clamp(30.693px, 1.918rem + ((1vw - 3.2px) * 2.285), 54px);px;">Never miss an episode</h3>



<p class="margin-bottom-half has-text-color" style="color:#ffffff;font-size:clamp(14px, 0.875rem + ((1vw - 3.2px) * 0.392), 18px);px;">Subscribe wherever you enjoy podcasts:</p>



<div class="wp-block-buttons margin-top-none is-layout-flex wp-block-buttons-is-layout-flex">
<div class="wp-block-button is-style-outline is-style-outline--6"><a class="wp-block-button__link has-text-color" href="https://podcasts.apple.com/us/podcast/stories-for-earth-with-forrest-brown/id1478061144" style="color:#ffffff;" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Apple</a></div>



<div class="wp-block-button is-style-outline is-style-outline--7"><a class="wp-block-button__link has-text-color" href="https://open.spotify.com/show/1p08YiP5SoxJEoFJyeebxR" style="color:#ffffff;" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Spotify</a></div>



<div class="wp-block-button is-style-outline is-style-outline--8"><a class="wp-block-button__link has-text-color" href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCGmH6FisTges9AzQlfbg-hg" style="color:#ffffff;" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">YouTube</a></div>



<div class="wp-block-button is-style-outline is-style-outline--9"><a class="wp-block-button__link has-text-color" href="https://www.stitcher.com/s?fid=463345&amp;refid=stpr" style="color:#ffffff;" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Stitcher</a></div>



<div class="wp-block-button is-style-outline is-style-outline--10"><a class="wp-block-button__link has-text-color" href="https://anchor.fm/s/113fd96c/podcast/rss" style="color:#ffffff;" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">RSS</a></div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div></div>



<hr class="wp-block-separator" />



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Overview</h2>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="255" height="400" src="/wp-content/uploads/2020/02/pacific-edge-book-cover.jpg?w=255" alt="The book cover for Pacific Edge by Kim Stanley Robinson." class="wp-image-712" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2020/02/pacific-edge-book-cover.jpg 255w, /wp-content/uploads/2020/02/pacific-edge-book-cover-191x300.jpg 191w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 255px) 100vw, 255px" /></figure>



<p><em>Pacific Edge</em> by Kim Stanley Robinson (<a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://bookshop.org/a/140/9780312890384" target="_blank">buy on Bookshop from $22.07</a>) is a work of utopian eco-fiction set in Orange County, California during the 2060s. Originally published in 1990 as part of the <em>Three Californias</em> <a rel="noreferrer noopener" aria-label="triptych (opens in a new tab)" href="https://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/triptych" target="_blank">triptych</a>, <em>Pacific Edge</em> includes many <a rel="noreferrer noopener" aria-label="solar punk themes (opens in a new tab)" href="https://dragonfly.eco/what-is-solarpunk/" target="_blank">solarpunk themes</a> such as energy independence through renewables, flourishing of local communities, green infrastructure and high technology, and strict government regulations limiting the power and size of corporations. The other two books in the triptych depict alternate futures for California—one struggling through a nuclear winter (<em>The Wild Shore</em>) and one being crushed by extreme wealth inequality caused by a giant tech boom (<em>The Gold Coast</em>). <em>Pacific Edge</em> takes a different route, using utopia as the setting with the still-fresh memory of a past dystopia threatening to return.</p>



<p>→ <a href="https://bookshop.org/a/140/9780312890384" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Buy on Bookshop from $22.07</a> (affiliate)</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator" />



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="top">Jump to</h2>



<ol class="wp-block-list"><li><a href="#about">About Kim Stanley Robinson</a></li><li><a href="#transcript">Transcript</a></li><li><a href="#recommendations">Recommendations</a></li></ol>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="about">About the creator</h2>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="460" height="480" src="/wp-content/uploads/2020/02/460px-kim_stanley_robinson_by_gage_skidmore_2.jpg?w=288" alt="Kim Stanley Robinson speaking at an event in Phoenix, Arizona." class="wp-image-720" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2020/02/460px-kim_stanley_robinson_by_gage_skidmore_2.jpg 460w, /wp-content/uploads/2020/02/460px-kim_stanley_robinson_by_gage_skidmore_2-288x300.jpg 288w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 460px) 100vw, 460px" /><figcaption>By Gage Skidmore, CC BY-SA 3.0, <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/w/index.php?curid=72961714" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener" aria-label="https://commons.wikimedia.org/w/index.php?curid=72961714 (opens in a new tab)">https://commons.wikimedia.org/w/index.php?curid=72961714</a></figcaption></figure>



<p>Kim Stanley Robinson is a literary science fiction writer from Davis, California. Born in Waukegan, Illinois in 1952, Robinson moved to Southern California as a child but has also lived in Washington, D.C. and Switzerland. His books frequently incorporate themes of climate change, sustainability, nature, environmental justice, and critiques of capitalism. The author of over 19 books and numerous short stories, Robinson has been awarded the <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="http://www.thehugoawards.org/" target="_blank">Hugo</a>, <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://nebulas.sfwa.org/" target="_blank">Nebula</a>, and <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://clarkeaward.com/" target="_blank">Arthur C. Clarke Awards</a> for his literary contributions to science fiction. He holds a BA in literature from UC San Diego, an MA in English from Boston University, and a PhD in English from UC San Diego, and he has taught at UC Davis and the <a rel="noreferrer noopener" aria-label="Clarion Science Fiction and Fantasy Writers' Workshop (opens in a new tab)" href="http://clarion.ucsd.edu/" target="_blank">Clarion Science Fiction and Fantasy Writers&#8217; Workshop</a>. His new novel <em>The Ministry for the Future</em> will be published in fall 2020.</p>



<p><strong>Official website:</strong> <a href="https://www.kimstanleyrobinson.info/">https://www.kimstanleyrobinson.info/</a></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="transcript">Transcript</h2>



<p><a href="#top">Back to top ↑</a></p>



<p>I’m Forrest Brown, and you’re listening to <em>Stories for Earth</em>.</p>



<p><em>[music: “Cold Descent” by Forrest Brown]</em></p>



<p>Welcome to <em>Stories for Earth</em>, a climate change podcast where we discuss stories that can give us strength and resilience in fighting the climate crisis. I’m glad you’re joining us today for the last episode of our first season.</p>



<p>For a transcript of today’s show, more information about the author, recommendations for further reading, and links to buy the book that we’ll be talking about today, visit our website at storiesforearth.com. That’s storiesforearth.com.</p>



<p>Today, we’ll be building off our discussion from last month by talking about Kim Stanley Robinson’s 1990 science fiction novel <em>Pacific Edge</em>, part of the <em>Three Californias</em> triptych. If you don’t like spoilers, now would be the time to turn off the podcast, read the book, and come back to finish the episode when you’re done.</p>



<p>But whatever order you decide to do things in, I hope you enjoy the show today.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">&#8220;Pacific Edge&#8221; plot summary</h2>



<p><a href="#top">Back to top ↑</a></p>



<p>I want you to imagine that you live in Southern California, in Orange County. Maybe you already do. The year is 2065, and apart from the time difference, most of your story could be happening today. Your job is renovating old houses. You have just won an election to serve in the local government. You’re in your early thirties, and you are in love for the first time.</p>



<p>The subject of your infatuation just separated from their partner of 15 years. Until now, you thought they’d only seen you as a friend. But now after the breakup, things are different. They start approaching you, wanting to spend time with you, inviting you on solo walks and flights around the county. The two of you begin to fall in love, and, for a while, life is good. It almost seems too good.</p>



<p>You see, your lover’s ex just so happens to be the town’s mayor and the CEO of a highly successful medical technology company. Shortly after you begin your term as an elected official, the mayor proposes rezoning a parcel of land that’s set aside for a park. They want to use the land to build a new commercial building for their company, even though your political party has worked hard for years to protect the land and leave it as wilderness. Oh, and the land is the hill that’s practically in your backyard.</p>



<p>Obviously, you want to fight this proposal, but think of how it will look considering you’re sleeping with the mayor’s recent ex-lover. And speaking of which, think, too, about the way this will look to your lover. Will they think you’re simply trying to rub it in the mayor’s face? Will they resent you for fighting against the zoning proposal with everything you’ve got? This is a tricky situation, and to get what you want, you’ll have to navigate it carefully, all while trying to act naturally. You’re angry, frustrated, and torn. Don’t you live in a beautiful place? Aren’t you surrounded by friends? Isn’t this supposed to be a utopia?</p>



<p>This is the plot of Kim Stanley Robinson’s novel <em>Pacific Edge</em>. Originally published in 1990—two years before Daniel Quinn told us we need to move beyond a “vision of doom”—<em>Pacific Edge</em> is a work of utopian ecological fiction that paints a portrait of what Southern California could look like if humans take swift and appropriate action to mitigate and adapt to climate change. The book is part of a triptych—a picture in three parts—that offers ideas about three different possible futures for California. One book depicts a future California struggling through a nuclear winter, another depicts a technocratic future marked by extreme income inequality, and the third, <em>Pacific Edge</em>, shows a hopeful future, one where humans have learned to live in harmony with the environment, limit growth, and work on restoring places wrecked by years of overdevelopment, overconsumption, and overpopulation.</p>



<p>At this point, it might be helpful for you to go back and listen to our previous episode on <em>Ishmael</em> by Daniel Quinn. You can still get something meaningful from today’s discussion without knowing about <em>Ishmael</em>, but I think <em>Pacific Edge</em> seems much more timely and important when discussed with <em>Ishmael</em> fresh in your memory. You can take this opportunity to press pause and come back to this episode, or continue listening to hear about Kim Stanley Robinson’s utopia.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">There is no such thing as a pocket utopia</h2>



<p><a href="#top">Back to top ↑</a></p>



<p>The word “utopia” comes to us from Sir Thomas Moore, who created the word for his 1516 book of the same name by <a href="https://www.etymonline.com/word/utopia" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener" aria-label=" (opens in a new tab)">joining together</a> two Greek words: <em>ou</em>, meaning “not,” and <em>topos</em>, meaning “place.” By definition, utopias are nowhere to be found. They do not exist. Intended to be a fictional imagination of a perfect world, the very word implies their impossibility. We live in a flawed world full of flawed people; a utopia can never exist.</p>



<p>But even though Wikipedia wasn’t a few keystrokes away in the late 80s, Kim Stanley Robinson was wise to this bit of knowledge when he wrote <em>Pacific Edge</em>. As we discover throughout the book, one of the main characters, Tom, wanted to write a utopia but found it impossible. A constant refrain marks his journal entries: “There is no such thing as a pocket utopia.” A pocket utopia. A small-scale, or island utopia, much like the very first imagining of such a place from Thomas Moore. But what about a utopia on a wider scale? Could that be possible?</p>



<p>The problem with utopias is that—so far, at least—they have all descended into dystopia, the exact opposite of what is supposed to be a perfect place. It turns out that not all visions of a perfect world are the same, and what may be heaven for one group of people is hell for another. Consider Communism in the 20th century. This was supposed to be a perfect society. It was supposed to fix all the problems caused by capitalism over the centuries before. But of course, we all know how that ended.</p>



<p>In China, the <a rel="noreferrer noopener" aria-label=" (opens in a new tab)" href="https://www.nytimes.com/2016/05/15/world/asia/china-cultural-revolution-explainer.html" target="_blank">Cultural Revolution</a> was an absolute disaster that killed millions of innocent people. In Russia, the rise of Vladimir Lenin and Joseph Stalin resulted in widespread killings, starvation, and poverty. By all accounts, Communism was an absolute failure. It might be the best modern example of why utopias are such a bad idea.</p>



<p>So why write a fictional utopia? Why read a fictional utopia? As I’ve already hinted at, Kim Stanley Robinson did his homework on utopias, and he didn’t fall for the same pitfalls that writers before him did. At worst, utopias kill people—as in Communist China and Soviet Russia—and at best, they’re just plain boring, as in the work of utopian fiction <em>Island</em> by Aldous Huxley. If everything is perfect, what is there to do? There can be nothing to work towards, nothing to fix, nothing to solve, nothing to improve, no conflict of any kind. While at first this may sound great, it begins to sound more and more like a definition of death. I don’t think anyone truly wants to live in a world like this.</p>



<p>But the vision of utopia that Robinson presents in <em>Pacific Edge </em>leans more into the “no place” meaning of the word than the “perfect place” meaning. This is a subtle but important distinction. <em>Pacific Edge</em> doesn’t make any pretenses about being able to <em>achieve</em> utopia; rather, it acknowledges that utopia is never an attainment but a striving. In a journal entry at the beginning of Chapter Four Tom writes:</p>



<p>&#8220;What a cheat utopias are, no wonder people hate them. Engineer some fresh start, an island, a new continent, dispossess them, give them a new planet sure! So they don’t have to deal with our history. Ever since More [sic] they’ve been doing it: rupture, clean cut, fresh start.</p>



<p>&#8220;So the utopias in books are pocket utopias too. Ahistorical, static, why should we read them? They don’t speak to us trapped in this world as we are, we look at them in the same way we look at the pretty inside of a paperweight, snow drifting down, so what? It may be nice but we’re stuck here and no one’s going to give us a fresh start, we have to deal with history as it stands, no freer than a wedge in a crack.</p>



<pre class="wp-block-verse">Stuck in history like a wedge in a crack
With no way out and no way back—
Split the world!</pre>



<p>&#8220;Must redefine utopia. It isn’t the perfect end-product of our wishes, define it so and it deserves the scorn of those who sneer when they hear the word. No. Utopia is the process of making a better world, the name for one path history can take, a dynamic, tumultuous, agonizing process, with no end. Struggle forever.</p>



<p>&#8220;Compare it to the present course of history. If you can.&#8221;</p>



<p>In Kim Stanley Robinson’s imagining of utopia, it must be ecumenical. And I use that word intentionally.</p>



<p>Ursula K. Le Guin—another utopian science fiction luminary and a huge influence of KSR’s who actually got a call out in the preceding quote—wrote many novels that took place in something she called the Ekumen. The Ekumen is a peaceful confederation of different planets that all work together for the advancement of humanity and the expanding of consciousness. We see a similar vision of this kind of utopian framework in Carl Sagan’s 1985 science fiction novel <em>Contact</em>. After receiving a series of extraterrestrial transmissions containing the blueprints for a vessel of interstellar travel, a group of scientists from Earth voyage to the center of the galaxy to meet representatives from alien races. The reason behind this meeting turns out to be for nothing other than sharing knowledge in the hopes of making every conscious being better off.</p>



<p>And this is where <em>Pacific Edge</em> truly shines: it gets at a similar kind of utopian society, although Earthbound. In order for humans to make any progress towards utopia, we must widen the scope of who and what we count as stakeholders. Call this society what you will—ecotopia, the Ekumen, the space station at the center of the Milky Way, the Kingdom of God, Earthseed—every one of them emphasizes embracing all living creatures and nature while working under the assumption that there is no one “right way” to live, as Daniel Quinn insists in <em>Ishmael</em>. “There is no such thing as a pocket utopia.” If a very small fraction of us live in palaces built on the rest of the world’s back, we have not achieved utopia.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">A practical utopia</h3>



<p>Talk about utopia seems to always bend towards the philosophical. And while philosophy is important, we’ll never make any progress in our journey towards utopia without also discussing the practical. In this regard, <em>Pacific Edge </em>walks and chews gum at the same time. The journal entries from Tom supply the philosophical context for why the world needs a utopian work of fiction, and the story of Kevin fighting the new zoning proposal provides the actual boots-on-the-ground examples of what striving for a utopia looks like. We can, in other words, work on building a utopia while we’re still trying to figure out just what exactly that means.</p>



<p>The story focuses mainly on Kevin’s attempts to thwart the mayor, Alfredo, from building a massive development on the hill behind Kevin’s house, but to me, Tom is the most interesting character in the book. Tom is Kevin’s grandfather and a retired lawyer, and while we don’t find out until later on that he wrote the journal entries preceding many chapters, Kevin does let us know from the beginning that Tom played a very important role in helping their town make good progress on reducing its carbon footprint. In fact, as the story goes on, we learn that Tom was a key lawyer in drafting many of the laws that put international limits on the size of corporations, the populations of towns and cities, and the amount of excess water that communities can store.</p>



<p>But Tom didn’t start out so successful. At the beginning of Chapter Two when we read his first journal entry, we learn that he’s living in Zürich, Switzerland in the 2010s while his wife works on her PhD. A so-called “pocket utopia” itself, Switzerland’s society is really starting to feel the pressure from the sudden and massive influx of refugees from natural disasters and armed conflicts around the world. Of course, these are all side effects of climate change, as Tom notes that the world’s climate has increased another degree Celsius above the pre-industrial average and that more and more species are going extinct every year.</p>



<p>All of this combined is causing a rise in Swiss nationalism and far-right politics. “Return Switzerland to the Swiss!” becomes a common chant, and soon Tom and his wife get a letter from the <em>Fremdenkontrolle der Stadt Zürich</em>—The Stranger Control—which results in Tom’s deportation back to the United States. But even after he arrives home, Tom is greeted with hostility from the American government. Classified as a radical anti-capitalist (and therefore anti-American), Tom is imprisoned and quarantined after a federal immigration agency fabricates HIV-positive test results for him.</p>



<p>Writing some of his later journal entries from prison, Tom scraps his ideas to write a utopia and rededicates himself to fighting for a better future on the same front from before his time in Switzerland—the legal system. After decades of hard-won legal battles, Tom emerges as the leader of the newly formed Green Party and leads America and the rest of the world in mitigating the worst effects of climate change and putting adaptation strategies into place.</p>



<p>Tom effectively helped save the world, so when Alfredo, the town’s mayor, tries to build on Kevin’s hill, Tom joins Kevin in trying to stop the proposal from passing. At the end of the book after Kevin and his friends fail to stop Alfredo, it’s Tom who finally manages to save the hill once and for all. Tom dies in a shipwreck right before Alfredo starts construction, and the town council votes to turn the hill into a memorial for Tom. This halts not only this one development but all future developments from destroying the delicate ecosystem on Kevin’s hill. The situation seemed very grim, but the characters fought tirelessly against regressing. It’s a hard-earned victory, but they win nevertheless.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading">A positive self-fulfilling prophecy</h3>



<p>You probably already know where I’m going with this. We are, right now, in the same position Tom was in when he decided to stop writing his utopian novel. In Europe, the Syrian refugee crisis prompted a bolstering and resurgence of nationalism, xenophobia, and outright Nazism, in some cases, with the rise of parties like the National Rally party in France and the Alternative for Germany (AfD) party. Here in the United States, Central American refugees are traveling up through Mexico to seek asylum in our country, something many Americans have shamefully chosen to use as fuel to throw on the fires of nationalism and racism. Whether they’re chanting “America First” or “Blood and Soil,” it all boils down to the same thing.</p>



<p>Within the past ten years, far-right, populist politics have swelled in popularity, the world’s climate has continued on a terrifying heating trend, the oceans have become hotter and more acidic, and more and more species have passed under the crosshairs of extinction. We live in a fraught time, and our actions today and every day have a huge impact on what the world will look like in ten and twenty years, but also in one, two, and five years since we are now experiencing very dangerous effects of global climate change.</p>



<p>In such a time, becoming overwhelmed and hopeless is the status quo, but we must buckle down and fight this feeling if we want to save our future. We hear frightening stories of dystopia all the time that confirm our worst fears about what the future will be like. We devour books like <em>The Handmaid’s Tale</em> and <em>The Hunger Games</em> with a rapacious appetite, but what if we dared to dream of something better, something that looks more like a utopia? Sure, the bad guys never win at the end of these books. If they did, no one would read them. But these stories always begin in a world where the bad guys <em>have</em> already won. It’s up to the heroes to restore justice and goodness to the world.</p>



<p>What if, instead, we set our sights on a future where the good guys won and the bad guys are the very last of a dying breed. I am usually one to shy away from what could turn out to be self-fulfilling prophecies, but in this situation, I think a positive self-fulfilling prophecy could do us all a lot of good. The characters in <em>Pacific Edge </em>may be fictional, but they are a perfect representation of this idea. Tom found the drive to create the future he envisioned only because he thought it was possible, only because he’d already imagined how that future would be.</p>



<p>If it weren’t for Tom and the hundreds if not thousands of other people who fought alongside him, Kevin wouldn’t have even been thrown into a situation where he had to push back against something as seemingly inconsequential as a new zoning proposal. Kevin’s world might still be imperfect to him, but to us reading about it today, it seems closer to utopia than anything else we’ve seen, and that gives us something to work with.</p>



<p>Tom teaches us that now is not the time for despair. Nor is it the time to give up. Now is the time to work our asses off.</p>



<p><em>[music: “Cold Descent” by Forrest Brown]</em></p>



<p><em>Stories for Earth</em> is written and produced by me, Forrest Brown. The intro and outro music is also by me. If you want to learn more about what we’re up to, you can find us on Instagram at <a href="https://www.instagram.com/storiesforearth/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener" aria-label="@storiesforearth (opens in a new tab)">@storiesforearth</a> and on Twitter at <a href="https://twitter.com/stories4earth" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener" aria-label="@stories4earth (opens in a new tab)">@stories4earth</a>. That’s the word “stories,” the number “4,” and the word “earth.” Our website is storiesforearth.com, where you can also find links to support us financially through Patreon and through our Bookshop.org page.</p>



<p>Thank you so much for joining us on our first season. Things will be quiet over here for a couple of months as my wife, our cat, and I get ready to move across the country from Nashville, Tennessee to Portland, Oregon, but we’ll be back very soon with more stories that can give us strength to fight climate change. Until then, thanks for listening.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="recommendations">Recommendations</h2>



<p><a href="#top">Back to top ↑</a></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-medium"><a href="https://bookshop.org/a/140/9781598536034" target="_blank"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="252" height="400" src="/wp-content/uploads/2020/02/always-coming-home-cover.jpg?w=189" alt="The book cover for Always Coming Home by Ursula K. Le Guin." class="wp-image-732" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2020/02/always-coming-home-cover.jpg 252w, /wp-content/uploads/2020/02/always-coming-home-cover-189x300.jpg 189w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 252px) 100vw, 252px" /></a></figure>



<p><strong>Book:</strong> <em>Always Coming Home</em> by Ursula K. Le Guin</p>



<p>→ <a href="https://bookshop.org/a/140/9781598536034" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener" aria-label="Buy on Bookshop from $31.50 (opens in a new tab)">Buy on Bookshop from $31.50</a> (affiliate)</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator" />



<figure class="wp-block-image size-medium"><a href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/a-sci-fi-authors-boldest-vision-of-climate-change-surviving-it-11581004678" target="_blank"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="1112" height="556" src="/wp-content/uploads/2020/02/a-sci-fi-authors-boldest-vision-of-climate-change-surviving-it.png?w=300" alt="A photo of Kim Stanley Robinson standing among some trees." class="wp-image-736" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2020/02/a-sci-fi-authors-boldest-vision-of-climate-change-surviving-it.png 1112w, /wp-content/uploads/2020/02/a-sci-fi-authors-boldest-vision-of-climate-change-surviving-it-300x150.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2020/02/a-sci-fi-authors-boldest-vision-of-climate-change-surviving-it-1024x512.png 1024w, /wp-content/uploads/2020/02/a-sci-fi-authors-boldest-vision-of-climate-change-surviving-it-768x384.png 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 1112px) 100vw, 1112px" /></a></figure>



<p><strong>Article:</strong> &#8220;A Sci-Fi Author&#8217;s Boldest Vision of Climate Change: Surviving It&#8221; by Russell Gold in the <em><a href="https://www.wsj.com/articles/a-sci-fi-authors-boldest-vision-of-climate-change-surviving-it-11581004678" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener" aria-label="Wall Street Journal (opens in a new tab)">Wall Street Journal</a></em> (paywall)</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator" />



<figure class="wp-block-image size-medium"><a href="https://bookshop.org/a/140/9780998702292" target="_blank"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="267" height="400" src="/wp-content/uploads/2020/02/solar-punk.jpg?w=200" alt="Book cover of Solarpunk by Fabio Fernandes, Gerson Lodi-Ribeiro, and Carlos Orsi." class="wp-image-738" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2020/02/solar-punk.jpg 267w, /wp-content/uploads/2020/02/solar-punk-200x300.jpg 200w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 267px) 100vw, 267px" /></a></figure>



<p><strong>Book:</strong> <em>Solarpunk: Ecological and Fantastical Stories in a Sustainable World</em> by Fabio Fernandes, Gerson Lodi-Ribeiro, and Carlos Orsi</p>



<p>→ <a href="https://bookshop.org/a/140/9780998702292" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener" aria-label="Buy on Bookshop from $13.75 (opens in a new tab)">Buy on Bookshop from $13.75</a> (affiliate)</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator" />



<figure class="wp-block-image size-medium"><a href="https://bookshop.org/a/140/9781597142939" target="_blank"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="275" height="400" src="/wp-content/uploads/2020/02/ecotopia.jpg?w=206" alt="" class="wp-image-741" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2020/02/ecotopia.jpg 275w, /wp-content/uploads/2020/02/ecotopia-206x300.jpg 206w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 275px) 100vw, 275px" /></a></figure>



<p>Book: <em>Ecotopia</em> by Ernest Callenbach</p>



<p>→ <a href="https://bookshop.org/a/140/9781597142939" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener" aria-label="Buy on Bookshop from $12.88 (opens in a new tab)">Buy on Bookshop from $12.88</a> (affiliate)</p>



<div class="wp-block-group alignfull"><div class="wp-block-group__inner-container is-layout-flow wp-block-group-is-layout-flow">
<div class="wp-block-coblocks-hero alignfull coblocks-hero-82610395659"><div class="wp-block-coblocks-hero__inner has-background hero-center-left-align has-padding has-huge-padding has-left-content" style="background-color:#f3f3f3;min-height:500px;"><div class="wp-block-coblocks-hero__content-wrapper"><div class="wp-block-coblocks-hero__content" style="max-width:560px;">
<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Like what you see? Become a Patreon member today for as little as $1 a month.</h2>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.patreon.com/storiesforearth" target="_blank"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="434" height="102" src="/wp-content/uploads/2020/12/become_a_patron_button402x.png?w=434" alt="" class="wp-image-1007" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2020/12/become_a_patron_button402x.png 434w, /wp-content/uploads/2020/12/become_a_patron_button402x-300x71.png 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 434px) 100vw, 434px" /></a></figure>
</div></div></div></div>
</div></div>
<p>The post <a href="/2020/02/25/pacific-edge-kim-stanley-robinson/">&#8220;Pacific Edge&#8221; by Kim Stanley Robinson: A Future Mythology</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Stories for Earth</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
