<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Stories for Earth</title>
	<atom:link href="/tag/season-3/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>/</link>
	<description>Stories for Earth is a climate change podcast that critically engages with stories that can teach us strength and resilience in fighting the climate crisis.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 18 Dec 2024 16:28:23 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.7.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>&#8220;New York 2140&#8221; by Kim Stanley Robinson: Summary &#038; Analysis</title>
		<link>/2022/01/03/new-york-2140-kim-stanley-robinson/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Forrest Brown]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 03 Jan 2022 19:41:14 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Episodes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[books]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[kim stanley robinson]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[season 3]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://storiesforearth.com/?p=1704</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>New York 2140 is the story of how a future New York City adapts to climate change and works to build a better world.</p>
<p>The post <a href="/2022/01/03/new-york-2140-kim-stanley-robinson/">&#8220;New York 2140&#8221; by Kim Stanley Robinson: Summary &amp; Analysis</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Stories for Earth</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><em>Stories for Earth relies on contributions from our listeners and readers to produce high quality, in-depth content. If you buy something using the links on our website, we may</em> <em>earn a small commission, at no extra cost to you. <em>For more information</em>, see our <a href="https://storiesforearth.com/affiliate-disclosure/">Affiliate Disclosure</a>.</em></p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator" />



<p>Widely regarded as a masterpiece of climate fiction and solarpunk, <em>New York 2140</em> by Kim Stanley Robinson is a sprawling novel about how New York City has adapted to climate chaos in the 22nd century. In this special two-part episode, I&#8217;ll first offer a plot summary and list of characters, followed by analysis of major themes. This is a long book with a lot to teach us about what a better world could look like and how we might get there, so I&#8217;m excited to finally discuss it on the podcast!</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-rich is-provider-spotify wp-block-embed-spotify wp-embed-aspect-21-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="embed-spotify"><iframe title="Spotify Embed: S3 E3.0 &quot;New York 2140&quot; by Kim Stanley Robinson" style="border-radius: 12px" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/episode/2kgK4jaNGLMQkRnWCaIMQd?si=6f22659664544d38&#038;utm_source=oembed"></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-medium"><img fetchpriority="high" decoding="async" width="257" height="400" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/new-york-2140-cover.jpeg?w=193" alt="The book cover for New York 2140 by Kim Stanley Robinson." class="wp-image-1707" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/new-york-2140-cover.jpeg 257w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/01/new-york-2140-cover-193x300.jpeg 193w" sizes="(max-width: 257px) 100vw, 257px" /></figure>



<p>→ <a href="https://www.betterworldbooks.com/product/detail/New-York-2140-9780316262316" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Buy <strong>USED</strong> on Better World Books from $7.48</a><br>→ <a href="https://bookshop.org/a/140/9780316262316">Buy <strong>NEW</strong> on Bookshop from $16.55</a> (affiliate)<br>→ <a href="http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/993559833" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Find at your local library</a></p>



<div class="wp-block-cover alignfull has-background-dim has-background-gradient" style="background:linear-gradient(135deg,rgb(92,145,60) 0%,rgb(169,209,153) 100%);min-height:350px;aspect-ratio:unset;"><div class="wp-block-cover__inner-container is-layout-flow wp-block-cover-is-layout-flow">
<div class="wp-block-jetpack-layout-grid alignfull column1-desktop-grid__span-10 column1-desktop-grid__start-2 column1-desktop-grid__row-1 column1-tablet-grid__span-8 column1-tablet-grid__row-1 column1-mobile-grid__span-4 column1-mobile-grid__row-1 wp-block-jetpack-layout-gutter__medium">
<div class="wp-block-jetpack-layout-grid-column wp-block-jetpack-layout-grid__padding-none">
<h3 class="has-text-color wp-block-heading" style="color:#ffffff;font-size:clamp(30.693px, 1.918rem + ((1vw - 3.2px) * 2.285), 54px);px;">Never miss an episode</h3>



<p class="margin-bottom-half has-text-color" style="color:#ffffff;font-size:clamp(14px, 0.875rem + ((1vw - 3.2px) * 0.392), 18px);px;">Subscribe wherever you enjoy podcasts:</p>



<div class="wp-block-buttons margin-top-none is-layout-flex wp-block-buttons-is-layout-flex">
<div class="wp-block-button is-style-outline is-style-outline--1"><a class="wp-block-button__link has-text-color" href="https://podcasts.apple.com/us/podcast/stories-for-earth-with-forrest-brown/id1478061144" style="color:#ffffff;" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Apple</a></div>



<div class="wp-block-button is-style-outline is-style-outline--2"><a class="wp-block-button__link has-text-color" href="https://open.spotify.com/show/1p08YiP5SoxJEoFJyeebxR" style="color:#ffffff;" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Spotify</a></div>



<div class="wp-block-button is-style-outline is-style-outline--3"><a class="wp-block-button__link has-text-color" href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCGmH6FisTges9AzQlfbg-hg" style="color:#ffffff;" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">YouTube</a></div>



<div class="wp-block-button is-style-outline is-style-outline--4"><a class="wp-block-button__link has-text-color" href="https://www.stitcher.com/s?fid=463345&amp;refid=stpr" style="color:#ffffff;" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Stitcher</a></div>



<div class="wp-block-button is-style-outline is-style-outline--5"><a class="wp-block-button__link has-text-color" href="https://anchor.fm/s/113fd96c/podcast/rss" style="color:#ffffff;" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">RSS</a></div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div></div>



<hr class="wp-block-separator" />



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="top">Jump to</h2>



<ol class="wp-block-list"><li><a href="#about">About Kim Stanley Robinson</a></li><li><a href="#transcript">Transcript</a><ol><li><a href="#introduction-to-new-york-2140">Introduction to &#8220;New York 2140&#8221;</a></li><li><a href="#summary-of-new-york-2140">Summary of &#8220;New York 2140&#8221;</a><ol><li><a href="#setting">Setting</a></li><li><a href="#character-list">Character list</a></li><li><a href="#plot-summary">Plot summary</a></li></ol></li><li><a href="#outro">Outro</a></li></ol></li><li><a href="#recommendations">Recommendations</a></li></ol>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="about">About the creator</h2>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-medium"><img decoding="async" width="460" height="480" src="/wp-content/uploads/2020/02/460px-kim_stanley_robinson_by_gage_skidmore_2.jpg?w=288" alt="" class="wp-image-720" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2020/02/460px-kim_stanley_robinson_by_gage_skidmore_2.jpg 460w, /wp-content/uploads/2020/02/460px-kim_stanley_robinson_by_gage_skidmore_2-288x300.jpg 288w" sizes="(max-width: 460px) 100vw, 460px" /><figcaption>By Gage Skidmore, CC BY-SA 3.0,&nbsp;<a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/w/index.php?curid=72961714" target="_blank">https://commons.wikimedia.org/w/index.php?curid=72961714</a></figcaption></figure>



<p>Kim Stanley Robinson is a literary science fiction writer from Davis, California. Born in Waukegan, Illinois in 1952, Robinson moved to Southern California as a child but has also lived in Washington, D.C. and Switzerland. His books frequently incorporate themes of climate change, sustainability, nature, environmental justice, and critiques of capitalism. The author of over 19 books and numerous short stories, Robinson has been awarded the&nbsp;<a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="http://www.thehugoawards.org/" target="_blank">Hugo</a>,&nbsp;<a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://nebulas.sfwa.org/" target="_blank">Nebula</a>, and&nbsp;<a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://clarkeaward.com/" target="_blank">Arthur C. Clarke Awards</a>&nbsp;for his literary contributions to science fiction. He holds a BA in literature from UC San Diego, an MA in English from Boston University, and a PhD in English from UC San Diego, and he has taught at UC Davis and the&nbsp;<a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="http://clarion.ucsd.edu/" target="_blank">Clarion Science Fiction and Fantasy Writers’ Workshop</a>. His latest novel,&nbsp;<em>The Ministry for the Future,</em>&nbsp;was published in fall 2020.</p>



<p><strong>Official website:</strong>&nbsp;<a href="https://www.kimstanleyrobinson.info/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">https://www.kimstanleyrobinson.info/</a></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="transcript">Transcript</h2>



<p><a href="#top">Back to top ↑</a></p>



<p>I’m Forrest Brown, and you’re listening to <em>Stories for Earth</em>.</p>



<p><em>[music: “Cold Descent” by Forrest Brown]</em></p>



<p>You’re listening to Stories for Earth, a podcast about everything climate change in pop culture.</p>



<p>Today, we’re talking about Kim Stanley Robinson’s novel <em>New York 2140</em>. It’s a long one, so we’re covering it in two parts. You’re listening to part one, where we’ll provide a plot summary of the book. Part two will cover a discussion of major themes and will be available a few weeks after the release of part one.</p>



<p>If you’d like to support further production of the show, consider becoming a member on Patreon for as little as $1 per month. We’re on Twitter and Instagram, and our website is storiesforearth.com.</p>



<p>And now, here’s part one of our discussion of <em>New York 2140</em>. I hope you enjoy.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="introduction-to-new-york-2140">Introduction to &#8220;New York 2140&#8221;</h3>



<p><a href="#top">Back to top ↑</a></p>



<p><em>&#8220;The proletarian movement is the self-conscious, independent movement of the immense majority in the interest of the immense majority.&#8221; -Karl Marx and Friedrich Engels, </em>The Communist Manifesto</p>



<p><em>&#8220;Ecology without class struggle is gardening.&#8221; -Chico Mendes, Brazilian trade union leader and environmentalist</em></p>



<p>During the first year of the COVID-19 pandemic, the world’s 2,365 billionaires became $4 trillion—or 54 percent—richer, according to a March 2021 <a href="https://inequality.org/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/Report-GlobalBillionaires-March31-2021.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">analysis</a> from the Program on Inequality at the Institute for Policy Studies (IPS). While the pandemic has killed <a href="https://covid19.who.int/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">millions of people</a> around the world and <a href="https://www.cbsnews.com/news/oxfam-billionaire-wealth-poverty/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">doubled</a> the global poverty rate, it’s been kind to the world’s richest people, further widening the already gaping wealth disparity between the haves and the have-nots.</p>



<p>This should come as no surprise if you’re familiar with Naomi Klein’s 2007 book <em>The</em> <em>Shock Doctrine: The Rise of Disaster Capitalism</em>. <em>The Shock Doctrine</em> examines how capitalism has taken advantage of and benefitted from moments of crisis, subverting the popular narrative of free market capitalism’s peaceful triumph over the 20th century. From the collapse of the Soviet Union to the rise of the fascist dictator Augusto Pinochet in Chile to the 2003 US invasion of Iraq, Klein demonstrates how capitalism pounces on moments of social upheaval and extreme violence to create economic opportunity.</p>



<p><strong>Also read:</strong> <a href="https://storiesforearth.com/2020/02/25/pacific-edge-kim-stanley-robinson/">&#8220;Pacific Edge&#8221; by Kim Stanley Robinson: A Future Mythology</a></p>



<p>We’re seeing the Shock Doctrine at play in real time with the COVID-19 pandemic, and many people, myself included, believe we’ll see it again and again as extreme weather events made worse by climate change become more frequent. Given shifting messaging from capitalists and neoliberal politicians, you might say it’s already happening.</p>



<p>Take, for example, recent remarks made by venture capitalist John Doerr, in which he called climate change the “…largest economic opportunity of the 21st Century,” according to <a href="https://www.marketwatch.com/story/vc-legend-john-doerr-says-climate-change-brings-economic-opportunity-thats-bigger-than-the-internet-boom-11636466626" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><em>MarketWatch</em></a>. You can also see this in the way shipping companies are <a href="https://maritime-executive.com/article/melting-ice-caps-and-new-shipping-lanes" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">gushing</a> about melting Arctic ice opening up new shipping lanes for trade. Or for a more lengthy analysis, consider the 2014 book <em>Windfall: The Booming Business of Global Warming</em> by Mckenzie Funk.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="summary-of-new-york-2140">Summary of “New York 2140”</h2>



<p><a href="#top">Back to top ↑</a></p>



<p>But it’s not just captains of industry and heads of state who hear <em>cha-ching</em> when they think of climate change. Science fiction writer Kim Stanley Robinson has seen the writing on the wall for the next big money making crisis, writing his 2017 novel <em>New York 2140</em> about this very phenomenon and exploring a possible solution for escaping it.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="setting">Setting</h3>



<p><a href="#top">Back to top ↑</a></p>



<p>Set over a century in the future, <em>New York 2140</em> takes place after some of the most cataclysmic effects of climate change have been felt. Based on the extremely high sea level rise seen in the novel, it’s safe to assume the world has blown past the Paris Agreement target to limit global warming to 1.5ºC above the pre-industrial average. Much of Lower Manhattan is now partially submerged, with neighboring boroughs like Brooklyn almost totally drowned. The ultra-wealthy live Uptown in superscrapers—dizzyingly tall skyscrapers—and Wall Street is fleeing for higher ground in Denver, Colorado.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img decoding="async" width="512" height="205" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/512px-lower_manhattan_from_jersey_city_november_2014_panorama_2.jpeg?w=512" alt="A photo of the Lower Manhattan skyline as seen from New Jersey in 2014." class="wp-image-1725" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/512px-lower_manhattan_from_jersey_city_november_2014_panorama_2.jpeg 512w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/01/512px-lower_manhattan_from_jersey_city_november_2014_panorama_2-300x120.jpeg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 512px) 100vw, 512px" /><figcaption><a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Lower_Manhattan_from_Jersey_City_November_2014_panorama_2.jpg" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">King of Hearts / Wikimedia Commons / CC-BY-SA-3.0</a>, <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">CC BY-SA 3.0</a>, via Wikimedia Commons</figcaption></figure>



<p>Lower Manhattan is now known as “the intertidal,” where flooded roads have transformed into canals and skyscrapers have been converted into partially self-sustaining housing co-ops for the dwindling middle class. Those not fortunate enough to make it into one of these vertical villages survive by squatting in the crumbling ruins of shorter buildings, which now serve as poker chips for investors in a kind of climate-induced housing bubble.</p>



<p>Being a New York novel, finance plays a big role in this story, and it can be easy to feel lost at times if you don’t have a basic understanding of finance or economics. But more than anything, <em>New York 2140</em> is a massive exercise in worldbuilding, where Kim Stanley Robinson has seemingly imagined every conceivable aspect of a future New York and chosen to follow the lives of ten main characters over the course of about three years. While most of the characters are neighbors living quite different lives as residents of the Met Life Tower, four of them are lumped into pairs and another one represents the city itself as a character.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="character-list">Character list</h3>



<p><a href="#top">Back to top ↑</a></p>



<p>To briefly summarize, the characters are as follows:</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list"><li><strong>Mutt and Jeff—</strong>two unemployed financial analysts living in a hotello (a sort of pop-up tent) in the vertical farm of the Met Life Tower</li><li><strong>Inspector Gen—</strong>an NYPD investigator who works on cracking a series of mysterious and seemingly unrelated cases throughout the novel</li><li><strong>Franklin Garr—</strong>a cocky young hedge fund trader who becomes the mastermind behind the largest debt strike in history</li><li><strong>Vlade—</strong>a middle-aged Ukrainian immigrant who works as the superintendent of the Met Life Tower</li><li><strong>The Citizen—</strong>a somewhat Shakespearean character who embodies the voice of New York City, often providing helpful historical context and snarky comedic relief in what I can only hear as a classic Manhattan accent</li><li><strong>Amelia Black—</strong>a futuristic streamer of sorts who hosts an internet show where she rescues endangered species and moves them to more hospitable environments as the climate continues to make ecosystems shapeshift</li><li><strong>Charlotte Armstrong—</strong>the chairperson of the Met Life Tower housing cooperative who works for the Householders’ Union, an NGO working to help those in need secure housing</li><li><strong>Stefan and Roberto—</strong>two “water rat” young boys orphaned in the intertidal who have had to learn to fend for themselves and are obsessed with hunting for buried treasure</li></ul>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="plot-summary">Plot summary</h3>



<p><a href="#top">Back to top ↑</a></p>



<p><em>New York 2140 </em>is a sweeping novel that contains many subplots, but the overarching plot has to do with changing the global financial system for the good and transitioning to a post-capitalist economic system. Simple topics, I know. Stay with me.</p>



<p>The book starts with a sort of socialist realist version of a Statler and Waldorf skit from <em>The Muppet Show</em>. Jeff is lecturing Mutt on the problems with capitalism and how he has a plan to make tiny tweaks to what he has identified as the 16 financial laws that govern the global financial system. Thanks to computer access granted by a recent freelance project for Jeff’s cousin who works in finance, Jeff can actually deploy the code he’s written to change these laws and hopefully save the world from greed and exploitation in the process.</p>



<p>Except, right after Jeff pushes the code revisions, the two realize they’ve been caught and have to make a run for it. The men go missing, and Charlotte Armstrong—chairperson of the Met Life tower housing co-op—files a police report. While Inspector Gen gets started on the case, a peppy and opportunistic Franklin Garr boats to work at WaterPrice, a hedge fund firm that manages investments in sea level and housing securities.</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center" style="font-size:28px;"><strong>Has this info helped you?</strong></p>



<p class="has-text-align-center has-normal-font-size"><em>Stories for Earth is and always will be a free resource to help people imagine brighter futures through the material we discuss. It&#8217;s also created and paid for by one person! Apart from occasional affiliate revenue, donations from people like you is the only way Stories for Earth remains financially feasible.</em></p>



<div class="wp-block-button aligncenter"><a class="wp-block-button__link has-very-light-gray-color has-luminous-vivid-orange-background-color has-text-color has-background" href="https://www.patreon.com/storiesforearth" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Support on Patreon</a></div>



<p></p>



<div class="wp-block-buttons is-content-justification-center is-layout-flex wp-container-core-buttons-is-layout-2 wp-block-buttons-is-layout-flex">
<div class="wp-block-button is-style-fill"><a class="wp-block-button__link has-vivid-cyan-blue-background-color has-background" href="https://venmo.com/code?user_id=3241757261168640196" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Donate on Venmo</a></div>
</div>



<p>Franklin is somewhat of a wunderkind at WaterPrice thanks to his invention of something called the Intertidal Property Pricing Index, or the IPPI. This is where the book starts to lose some people since it can get a little technical with finance-talk, so I’ll do my best to explain it here.</p>



<p>In 2140, sea level rise is tracked religiously, thanks to the traumas of the past one-hundred-plus years when sea levels rose dramatically and rapidly, mostly in two events called the First and Second Pulse. These were episodes of massive sea level rise in a very short amount of time due to major collapses in the Antarctic and Greenland ice sheets. Both Pulses caused incalculable amounts of destruction to coastal communities around the world, and everyone is paranoid about the prospect of a Third Pulse happening.</p>



<p>True to form, Wall Street and other financial hubs found a way to make betting on sea level rise a lucrative business. Now, sea level has its own index on the stock market, just like the top 500 publicly traded companies have the S&amp;P 500 today. Housing has its own index as well. So, to put it simply, this index that Franklin Garr has created—the Intertidal Property Pricing Index—functions to produce an accurate, real-time price estimate of coastal property based on the global rise and fall of sea level.</p>



<p><strong>Also read:</strong> <a href="https://storiesforearth.com/2020/01/14/ishmael-daniel-quinn-climate-change/">&#8220;Ishmael&#8221; by Daniel Quinn, Climate Change, and Moving Beyond a Vision of Doom</a></p>



<p>This helps to explain why buildings in the intertidal zone of New York City are so valuable now. Even though the East Coast is largely drowned, people haven’t totally abandoned their homes, stubbornly sticking around through some drastic adaptation measures. The submerged ground floors of buildings are totally sealed off to prevent flooding, and buildings have been reinforced with <a href="https://www.digitaltrends.com/cool-tech/what-is-graphene/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">graphene</a> to keep them from tumbling into the polluted water.</p>



<p>However, this interest in betting on housing prices has led to a fiercely competitive housing market, which is causing some stress for Charlotte Armstrong. The Met Life tower housing co-op has recently learned of a bid from an unknown party to buy the building, and the size of the bid smells like an attempt at a hostile takeover. Forced to put the bid to a vote among the tower’s residents, the co-op narrowly avoids getting bought out, but Charlotte is rattled by this and determined to find out who’s behind the bid.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="512" height="683" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/512px-metropolitan_life_insurance_co_bldg_01.jpeg?w=225" alt="A photo of the Metropolitan Life Insurance building in New York City from 2008." class="wp-image-1723" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/512px-metropolitan_life_insurance_co_bldg_01.jpeg 512w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/01/512px-metropolitan_life_insurance_co_bldg_01-225x300.jpeg 225w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 512px) 100vw, 512px" /><figcaption><a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Metropolitan_Life_Insurance_Co_Bldg_01.jpg" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Gigi alt</a>, <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">CC BY-SA 3.0</a>, via Wikimedia Commons</figcaption></figure>



<p>To complicate things, it seems someone is trying to sabotage the Met Life tower. Vlade, the building’s superintendent, gets an alert early one morning of a leak in the building’s basement. Upon inspection, it appears someone has intentionally drilled through one of the walls facing the outside canal. Vlade manages to contain and patch the leak, but the event is still unsettling. Charlotte suspects whoever tried to buy the Met Life tower might be behind it.</p>



<p>Meanwhile, we’re introduced to Amelia Black, a “cloud” star who hosts a popular show called <em>Assisted Migration</em>, named after the giant airship she flies of the same name. Amelia is on a mission to relocate some starving polar bears to Antarctica, where conditions are still similar enough to their ideal environment to give them a chance at survival. Stefan and Roberto—two orphaned young boys who live in the canals—make an appearance after Franklin Garr saves them from drowning. Vlade takes them under his wing, and they eventually spill the beans about their plans to salvage the wreckage of an old British ship they’ve found and hopefully recover some sunken treasure.</p>



<p>Vlade goes on a couple of other treasure hunts with the boys, eventually employing the help of his ex-wife Idelba and her boat to recover the gold from the wreckage of the <em>HMS Hussar</em>. It’s on one of these expeditions that Vlade accidentally finds Mutt and Jeff, who have been held prisoner in a kind of underwater facility on the bottom of the bay. This gives Inspector Gen some new leads, who eventually narrows the list of suspects down to Jeff’s cousin, a hedge fund manager named Henry Vinson.</p>



<p>Seemingly unbeknownst to him, Vinson’s hedge fund, Albany Albany, hired a private security firm to kidnap Mutt and Jeff, though we later find out it was Charlotte’s ex-husband and chair of the Federal Reserve who ordered the kidnapping under the guise of placing them in witness protection. Mutt and Jeff’s rescue also provides some evidence that Vinson’s hedge fund was going through Morningside Realty in the attempted buy-out of the Met Life tower.</p>



<p>These discoveries are soon overshadowed by news that a massive hurricane is heading for New York City, and the residents of the Met Life tower scramble to prepare for what is likely to be a nasty storm. Amelia Black is forced to delay her return home, flying north to ride out the storm, and Stefan and Roberto go missing after they’re caught in the storm while trying to find the grave of Herman Melville, the author of <em>Moby Dick</em>.</p>



<p>The other main characters hunker down in the Met Life tower, which emerges relatively unscathed compared to some of the other nearby buildings. However, the intertidal zone where the poor live as squatters in crumbling buildings, is completely annihilated, and Vlade and his ex-wife Idelba venture out in her tugboat to save as many people as possible from the lethal storm surge.</p>



<p>In the aftermath of the hurricane, hundreds of people have perished, and thousands more are effectively climate refugees—now homeless and living in a massive open-air refugee camp in the wreckage of Central Park. Charlotte is overwhelmed with requests to the Householder’s Union, and she makes an unsuccessful attempt to convince the mayor to seize all the unused housing uptown that has been bought up by rich investors. A riot ensues after the refugees are essentially abandoned by the city, and the NYPD gets locked into a tense standoff with the same private security company who kidnapped Mutt and Jeff.</p>



<p>Inspector Gen manages to de-escalate the situation, but not without getting some important information on who the security company works for—Henry Vinson. By this point, Vinson’s name has been found to be connected to a number of mysteries throughout the novel, from the hostile buyout of the Met Life tower to Mutt and Jeff’s kidnapping to a private security firm threatening to shoot rioters attempting to breach a pretty much vacant building.</p>



<p>This eventually gets back to the hedge fund trader, Franklin Garr. Remembering a conversation he’d previously had with Charlotte Armstrong about how a debt strike could bring the global financial system to its knees to better serve everyday people, Franklin springs into action. He calls up Charlotte, and the two hatch a plan to make the debt strike a reality. Amelia Black also gets in on the action, using her enormous platform as a cloud star to send the rallying cry.</p>



<p>What is this debt strike? It’s basically an intentional recreation of the 2008 financial crisis. If you recall, the 2008 financial crisis happened because a housing bubble collapsed in the United States. This caused a domino effect of economic consequences that resulted in the global Great Recession.</p>



<p>In very simple terms, banks approved a lot of predatory mortgages to people who most likely could not afford them. And by that I mean they started issuing mortgages like what they called “No Income, No Assets” or Ninja loans. When these people inevitably couldn’t make payments on their mortgages anymore, thousands of houses went into foreclosure, and behemoth investment banks like Bear Stearns went bankrupt. If you want a really entertaining and accessible explanation of what happened, I highly recommend the movie <em>The Big Short</em>.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-16-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="embed-youtube"><iframe loading="lazy" title="The Big Short Trailer (2015) ‐ Paramount Pictures" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/vgqG3ITMv1Q?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p>This is essentially the kind of financial crisis Franklin, Charlotte, and Amelia helped orchestrate. Except this time, mortgage payments stopped because hundreds of thousands of people made a choice to stop paying them all at the same time rather than being forced to stop making payments out of financial necessity. Just as they hoped, this caused a domino effect that brought the global financial system down. The banks asked for a government bailout, but this time was different from the series of stimulus packages Congress passed in 2009.</p>



<p>Governments around the world still bailed out financial institutions but in exchange for nationalization. In other words, governments gave them the cash they needed to survive on the condition that the money go towards buying shares. This effectively made governments around the world majority shareholders in the various failing financial institutions, thereby netting them a lot of revenue for their national budgets.</p>



<p>What happens next is a bit of a blur. With bolstered confidence from the successful nationalization of Wall Street, Congress passed a flurry of legislation straight from a progressive Democrat’s wildest dreams: universal healthcare, free college tuition, full employment, programs, aggressive environmental protections, a corporate tax rate of 90 percent, laws preventing capital flight to tax havens, et cetera.</p>



<p>Thus ends <em>New York 2140</em>. It’s a long and wild ride with lots to say about the fundamental brokenness of our current neoliberal era marked by extreme wealth inequality, climate breakdown, fascism, and disaster capitalism. And yet, despite a tendency to pontificate and perhaps lean too heavily on historical events from the early 21st century, it’s a pleasant and engaging read that has a lot to teach us about human resiliency and the power of collective action.</p>



<h3 class="wp-block-heading" id="outro">Outro</h3>



<p><a href="#top">Back to top ↑</a></p>



<p>I’m doing this episode a bit differently from past ones, so be on the lookout for part two of our episode on <em>New York 2140</em>, where we’ll move beyond a plot summary to analyze some of the major themes in the novel.</p>



<p>In the meantime, be sure to follow us on Twitter and Instagram, and check out our website at storiesforearth.com. If you’d like to support further production of the show, consider becoming a member on Patreon for as little as $1 per month.</p>



<p>Thanks for listening, and I’ll talk to you soon.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="recommendations">Recommendations</h2>



<p><a href="#top">Back to top ↑</a></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="255" height="400" src="/wp-content/uploads/2020/02/pacific-edge-book-cover.jpg?w=191" alt="" class="wp-image-712" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2020/02/pacific-edge-book-cover.jpg 255w, /wp-content/uploads/2020/02/pacific-edge-book-cover-191x300.jpg 191w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 255px) 100vw, 255px" /></figure>



<p><strong>Book:</strong> <em>Pacific Edge</em> by Kim Stanley Robinson</p>



<p>→ <a href="https://www.betterworldbooks.com/product/detail/Pacific-Edge---Three-Californias-9780312890384" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Buy <strong>USED</strong> on Better World Books from $5.44</a><br>→ <a href="https://bookshop.org/a/140/9780312890384" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Buy <strong>NEW</strong> on Bookshop from $22.07</a> (affiliate)<br>→ <a href="http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/1023125245" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Find at your local library</a></p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator" />



<figure class="wp-block-image size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="267" height="400" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/the-shock-doctrine-by-naomi-klein.jpeg?w=200" alt="Book cover for The Shock Doctrine by Naomi Klein." class="wp-image-1563" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/the-shock-doctrine-by-naomi-klein.jpeg 267w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/08/the-shock-doctrine-by-naomi-klein-200x300.jpeg 200w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 267px) 100vw, 267px" /></figure>



<p><strong>Book:</strong> <em>The Shock Doctrine: The Rise of Disaster Capitalism</em> by Naomi Klein</p>



<p>→ <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.betterworldbooks.com/product/detail/Shock-Doctrine---The-Rise-of-Disaster-Capitalism-9780312427993" target="_blank">Buy <strong>USED</strong> on Better World Books from $5.05</a> <br>→ <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://bookshop.org/a/140/9780312427993" target="_blank">Buy <strong>NEW</strong> on Bookshop from $20.24</a> (affiliate)<br>→ <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/1003865219" target="_blank">Find at your local library</a></p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator" />



<figure class="wp-block-image size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="267" height="400" src="/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/sunvault-book-cover.jpeg?w=200" alt="Book cover for Sunvault: Stories of Solarpunk and Eco-Speculation." class="wp-image-1718" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2022/01/sunvault-book-cover.jpeg 267w, /wp-content/uploads/2022/01/sunvault-book-cover-200x300.jpeg 200w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 267px) 100vw, 267px" /></figure>



<p><strong>Book:</strong> <em>Sunvault: Stories of Solarpunk and Eco-Speculation</em> edited by Phoebe Wagner and Brontë Christopher Wieland</p>



<p>→ <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://bookshop.org/a/140/9781937794750" target="_blank">Buy <strong>NEW</strong> on Bookshop from $12.87</a> (affiliate)<br>→ <a href="http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/1001569674" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Find at your local library</a></p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator" />



<p><strong>Article:</strong> &#8220;<a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://hieroglyph.asu.edu/2014/09/solarpunk-notes-toward-a-manifesto/" target="_blank">Solarpunk: Notes toward a manifesto</a>&#8221; by Adam Flynn in <em>Hieroglyph</em></p>



<div class="wp-block-group alignfull"><div class="wp-block-group__inner-container is-layout-flow wp-block-group-is-layout-flow">
<div class="wp-block-coblocks-hero alignfull coblocks-hero-82610395659"><div class="wp-block-coblocks-hero__inner has-background hero-center-left-align has-padding has-huge-padding has-left-content" style="background-color:#f3f3f3;min-height:500px;"><div class="wp-block-coblocks-hero__content-wrapper"><div class="wp-block-coblocks-hero__content" style="max-width:560px;">
<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Like what you see? Become a Patreon member today for as little as $1 a month.</h2>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.patreon.com/storiesforearth" target="_blank"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="434" height="102" src="/wp-content/uploads/2020/12/become_a_patron_button402x.png?w=434" alt="" class="wp-image-1007" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2020/12/become_a_patron_button402x.png 434w, /wp-content/uploads/2020/12/become_a_patron_button402x-300x71.png 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 434px) 100vw, 434px" /></a></figure>
</div></div></div></div>
</div></div>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="/2022/01/03/new-york-2140-kim-stanley-robinson/">&#8220;New York 2140&#8221; by Kim Stanley Robinson: Summary &amp; Analysis</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Stories for Earth</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>A Discussion of &#8220;The Day After Tomorrow&#8221; with Dr. Yanas Kisten</title>
		<link>/2021/11/01/the-day-after-tomorrow/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Forrest Brown]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 01 Nov 2021 18:59:34 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Episodes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[movies]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[season 3]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://storiesforearth.com/?p=1623</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The Day After Tomorrow is one of the biggest films ever made about climate change. Forrest and Yanas of Geekoscopy discuss the film in this special episode.</p>
<p>The post <a href="/2021/11/01/the-day-after-tomorrow/">A Discussion of &#8220;The Day After Tomorrow&#8221; with Dr. Yanas Kisten</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Stories for Earth</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><em>Stories for Earth relies on contributions from our listeners and readers to produce high quality, in-depth content. If you buy something using the links on our website, we may</em> <em>earn a small commission, at no extra cost to you. <em>For more information</em>, see our <a href="https://storiesforearth.com/affiliate-disclosure/">Affiliate Disclosure</a>.</em></p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator" />



<p>Seeing <em>The Day After Tomorrow</em> as a youth was probably the first time I was exposed to the idea of climate change. And 17 years later, this film remains one of the only major Hollywood productions to explicitly engage with the topic. For this special episode of <em>Stories for Earth</em>, I chatted with Dr. Yanas Kisten, a scientist and host of the podcast Geekoscopy, about one of our favorite disaster flicks: <em>The Day After Tomorrow</em>, directed by Roland Emmerich.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="206" height="305" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/the-day-after-tomorrow.jpeg?w=206" alt="The official movie poster for The Day After Tomorrow." class="wp-image-1625" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/the-day-after-tomorrow.jpeg 206w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/11/the-day-after-tomorrow-203x300.jpeg 203w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 206px) 100vw, 206px" /></figure>



<ul class="wp-block-list"><li><strong>Buy or rent on YouTube:</strong> <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://youtu.be/K_xwj9bHZm4" target="_blank">https://youtu.be/K_xwj9bHZm4</a></li></ul>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Special guest: Dr. Yanas Kisten, host of the Geekoscopy podcast</h2>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="684" height="559" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/dr-yanas-kisten.png?w=300" alt="Photo of Dr. Yanas Kisten, host of the Geekoscopy podcast." class="wp-image-1636" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/dr-yanas-kisten.png 684w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/11/dr-yanas-kisten-300x245.png 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 684px) 100vw, 684px" /></figure>



<p>For this episode, I&#8217;m joined by Dr. Yanas Kisten, a South African scientist and host of the Geekoscopy podcast, which explores “…the intersection between science, story, and play.” Yanas is a postdoctoral researcher at Nelson Mandela University in Eastern Cape, South Africa and is interested in science communication. He examines the many different ways that geek culture can help science reach a broader audience through his podcast.</p>



<ul class="wp-block-list"><li><strong>Website:</strong> <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.geekoscopy.com/" target="_blank">https://www.geekoscopy.com/</a></li><li><strong>Twitter:</strong> <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://twitter.com/geekoscopy" target="_blank">https://twitter.com/geekoscopy</a></li><li><strong>Instagram:</strong> <a href="https://www.instagram.com/geekoscopy/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">https://www.instagram.com/geekoscopy/</a></li></ul>



<div class="wp-block-cover alignfull has-background-dim has-background-gradient" style="background:linear-gradient(135deg,rgb(92,145,60) 0%,rgb(169,209,153) 100%);min-height:350px;aspect-ratio:unset;"><div class="wp-block-cover__inner-container is-layout-flow wp-block-cover-is-layout-flow">
<div class="wp-block-jetpack-layout-grid alignfull column1-desktop-grid__span-10 column1-desktop-grid__start-2 column1-desktop-grid__row-1 column1-tablet-grid__span-8 column1-tablet-grid__row-1 column1-mobile-grid__span-4 column1-mobile-grid__row-1 wp-block-jetpack-layout-gutter__medium">
<div class="wp-block-jetpack-layout-grid-column wp-block-jetpack-layout-grid__padding-none">
<h3 class="has-text-color wp-block-heading" style="color:#ffffff;font-size:clamp(30.693px, 1.918rem + ((1vw - 3.2px) * 2.285), 54px);px;">Never miss an episode</h3>



<p class="margin-bottom-half has-text-color" style="color:#ffffff;font-size:clamp(14px, 0.875rem + ((1vw - 3.2px) * 0.392), 18px);px;">Subscribe wherever you enjoy podcasts:</p>



<div class="wp-block-buttons margin-top-none is-layout-flex wp-block-buttons-is-layout-flex">
<div class="wp-block-button is-style-outline is-style-outline--6"><a class="wp-block-button__link has-text-color" href="https://podcasts.apple.com/us/podcast/stories-for-earth-with-forrest-brown/id1478061144" style="color:#ffffff;" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Apple</a></div>



<div class="wp-block-button is-style-outline is-style-outline--7"><a class="wp-block-button__link has-text-color" href="https://open.spotify.com/show/1p08YiP5SoxJEoFJyeebxR" style="color:#ffffff;" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Spotify</a></div>



<div class="wp-block-button is-style-outline is-style-outline--8"><a class="wp-block-button__link has-text-color" href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCGmH6FisTges9AzQlfbg-hg" style="color:#ffffff;" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">YouTube</a></div>



<div class="wp-block-button is-style-outline is-style-outline--9"><a class="wp-block-button__link has-text-color" href="https://www.stitcher.com/s?fid=463345&amp;refid=stpr" style="color:#ffffff;" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Stitcher</a></div>



<div class="wp-block-button is-style-outline is-style-outline--10"><a class="wp-block-button__link has-text-color" href="https://anchor.fm/s/113fd96c/podcast/rss" style="color:#ffffff;" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">RSS</a></div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div></div>



<hr class="wp-block-separator" />



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="top">Jump to</h2>



<ol class="wp-block-list"><li><a href="#about">About Roland Emmerich</a></li><li><a href="#transcript">Transcript</a></li><li><a href="#recommendations">Recommendations</a></li></ol>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="about">About the creator</h2>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="256" height="372" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/roland-emmerich.jpeg?w=256" alt="" class="wp-image-1629" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/roland-emmerich.jpeg 256w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/11/roland-emmerich-206x300.jpeg 206w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 256px) 100vw, 256px" /><figcaption>Source: <a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Independence_Day-_Resurgence_Japan_Premiere-_Roland_Emmerich_(28502013341)_CROPPED.jpg" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Dick Thomas Johnson</a>, <a href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">CC BY 2.0</a>, via Wikimedia Commons</figcaption></figure>



<p>Roland Emmerich is a German film director and producer known for movies like <em>The Day After Tomorrow</em> (2004), <em>Independence Day</em> (1996), and <em>The Patriot</em> (2000). Educated at the Munich Film and Television School, Emmerich&#8217;s career began with his student film, <em>The Noah&#8217;s Ark Principle</em> (1984), opening the 1984 Berlin Film Festival. The film was a success, paving the way for him to make his Hollywood directorial debut with <em>Universal Soldier</em> in 1992. Roland Emmerich lives in Los Angeles where he runs the film and television production company Centropolis Entertainment.</p>



<p><strong>Official website:</strong> <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="http://www.centropolis.com/" target="_blank">http://www.centropolis.com/</a><br><strong>Twitter: </strong><a href="https://twitter.com/rolandemmerich" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">https://twitter.com/rolandemmerich</a></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="transcript">Transcript</h2>



<p><a href="#top">Back to top ↑</a></p>



<p>*Coming soon*</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="recommendations">Recommendations</h2>



<p><a href="#top">Back to top ↑</a></p>



<p><strong>Article:</strong> &#8220;<a href="https://yaleclimateconnections.org/2014/11/the-long-melt-the-lingering-influence-of-the-day-after-tomorrow/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">The lingering influence of &#8216;Day After Tomorrow&#8217;</a>&#8221; by Michael Svoboda in <em>Yale Climate Connections</em></p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator" />



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-rich is-provider-spotify wp-block-embed-spotify wp-embed-aspect-21-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="embed-spotify"><iframe title="Spotify Embed: Stories for Earth! GKSP101 EP030: Forrest Brown" style="border-radius: 12px" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/episode/0QXl7b6m4lpvgmsZoParK4?si=h0s-kTyiQhCJPY0Yy1ZH9Q&#038;utm_source=oembed"></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Interview:</strong> Stories for Earth! GKSP101 EP030: Forrest Brown</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator" />



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-video is-provider-youtube wp-block-embed-youtube wp-embed-aspect-4-3 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="embed-youtube"><iframe loading="lazy" title="Everything Wrong With The Day After Tomorrow" width="500" height="281" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/CUpNcBSG-lg?feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" allowfullscreen></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p><strong>Video:</strong> Everything Wrong With The Day After Tomorrow from CinemaSins</p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator" />



<figure class="wp-block-image size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="400" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/gun-island-and-the-great-derangement.png?w=300" alt="An image of the book covers for The Great Derangement and Gun Island by Amitav Ghosh against a mangrove forest background." class="wp-image-1646" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2021/11/gun-island-and-the-great-derangement.png 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/11/gun-island-and-the-great-derangement-300x150.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/11/gun-island-and-the-great-derangement-768x384.png 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /></figure>



<p><strong>Podcast:</strong> &#8220;Gun Island&#8221; and &#8220;The Great Derangement&#8221; by Amitav Ghosh: Summary &amp; Analysis from <em>Stories for Earth</em></p>



<ul class="wp-block-list"><li><a href="https://storiesforearth.com/2021/04/15/gun-island-the-great-derangement-amitav-ghosh/">Transcript</a></li><li><a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://open.spotify.com/episode/3Vb5iZwCIleFEYMuW6Wm3J?si=JFe7MGCBScCt6k7TE0oB5g" target="_blank">Listen on Spotify</a></li><li><a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://podcasts.apple.com/us/podcast/stories-for-earth-climate-change-in-pop-culture/id1478061144?i=1000517248307" target="_blank">Listen on Apple Podcasts</a></li><li><a href="https://www.stitcher.com/show/stories-for-earth/episode/s2-e7-gun-island-and-the-great-derangement-by-amitav-ghosh-83208510" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Listen on Stitcher</a></li></ul>



<div class="wp-block-group alignfull"><div class="wp-block-group__inner-container is-layout-flow wp-block-group-is-layout-flow">
<div class="wp-block-coblocks-hero alignfull coblocks-hero-82610395659"><div class="wp-block-coblocks-hero__inner has-background hero-center-left-align has-padding has-huge-padding has-left-content" style="background-color:#f3f3f3;min-height:500px;"><div class="wp-block-coblocks-hero__content-wrapper"><div class="wp-block-coblocks-hero__content" style="max-width:560px;">
<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Like what you see? Become a Patreon member today for as little as $1 a month.</h2>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.patreon.com/storiesforearth" target="_blank"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="434" height="102" src="/wp-content/uploads/2020/12/become_a_patron_button402x.png?w=434" alt="" class="wp-image-1007" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2020/12/become_a_patron_button402x.png 434w, /wp-content/uploads/2020/12/become_a_patron_button402x-300x71.png 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 434px) 100vw, 434px" /></a></figure>
</div></div></div></div>
</div></div>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="/2021/11/01/the-day-after-tomorrow/">A Discussion of &#8220;The Day After Tomorrow&#8221; with Dr. Yanas Kisten</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Stories for Earth</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>&#8220;How Beautiful We Were&#8221; by Imbolo Mbue: Summary &#038; Analysis</title>
		<link>/2021/08/24/how-beautiful-we-were-imbolo-mbue/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Forrest Brown]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 24 Aug 2021 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Episodes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[books]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[season 3]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://storiesforearth.com/?p=1542</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>How Beautiful We Were by Imbolo Mbue is the story of one small African village as it fights for justice from an American oil company.</p>
<p>The post <a href="/2021/08/24/how-beautiful-we-were-imbolo-mbue/">&#8220;How Beautiful We Were&#8221; by Imbolo Mbue: Summary &amp; Analysis</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Stories for Earth</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><em>Stories for Earth relies on contributions from our listeners and readers to produce high quality, in-depth content. If you buy something using the links on our website, we may</em> <em>earn a small commission, at no extra cost to you. <em>For more information</em>, see our <a href="https://storiesforearth.com/affiliate-disclosure/">Affiliate Disclosure</a>.</em></p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator" />



<p>Set in the fictional African village of Kosawa, <em>How Beautiful We Were</em> by Imbolo Mbue is the story of a decades-long fight for environmental justice. The novel centers around the Nangi family, telling their story from multiple different perspectives over the course of the book. And though <em>How Beautiful We Were</em> takes place in a fictional African country, it bears a close resemblance to some important modern-day climate themes.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-rich is-provider-spotify wp-block-embed-spotify wp-embed-aspect-21-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="embed-spotify"><iframe title="Spotify Embed: S3 E1: How Beautiful We Were by Imbolo Mbue" style="border-radius: 12px" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/episode/5hTrtrBrq8zhc0fA3TaE3m?si=98655f098b5a4a5c&#038;utm_source=oembed"></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p>In our first episode of season three, we&#8217;ll take a look at a plot summary of this novel, exploring the characters, providing an in-depth analysis, and looking at current events in Ecuador as a possible real-life parallel. Listen wherever you get podcasts below, and consider buying your own copy using our affiliate link below. We appreciate the support!</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="523" height="799" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/how-beautiful-we-were-by-imbolo-mbue.png?w=196" alt="The book cover for How Beautiful We Were by Imbolo Mbue." class="wp-image-1554" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/how-beautiful-we-were-by-imbolo-mbue.png 523w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/08/how-beautiful-we-were-by-imbolo-mbue-196x300.png 196w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 523px) 100vw, 523px" /></figure>



<p>→ <a href="https://bookshop.org/a/140/9780593132425" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Buy <strong>NEW</strong> on Bookshop from $25.76</a> (affiliate)<br>→ <a href="http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/1240502427" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Find at your local library</a></p>



<div class="wp-block-cover alignfull has-background-dim has-background-gradient" style="background:linear-gradient(135deg,rgb(92,145,60) 0%,rgb(169,209,153) 100%);min-height:350px;aspect-ratio:unset;"><div class="wp-block-cover__inner-container is-layout-flow wp-block-cover-is-layout-flow">
<div class="wp-block-jetpack-layout-grid alignfull column1-desktop-grid__span-10 column1-desktop-grid__start-2 column1-desktop-grid__row-1 column1-tablet-grid__span-8 column1-tablet-grid__row-1 column1-mobile-grid__span-4 column1-mobile-grid__row-1 wp-block-jetpack-layout-gutter__medium">
<div class="wp-block-jetpack-layout-grid-column wp-block-jetpack-layout-grid__padding-none">
<h3 class="has-text-color wp-block-heading" style="color:#ffffff;font-size:clamp(30.693px, 1.918rem + ((1vw - 3.2px) * 2.285), 54px);px;">Never miss an episode</h3>



<p class="margin-bottom-half has-text-color" style="color:#ffffff;font-size:clamp(14px, 0.875rem + ((1vw - 3.2px) * 0.392), 18px);px;">Subscribe wherever you enjoy podcasts:</p>



<div class="wp-block-buttons margin-top-none is-layout-flex wp-block-buttons-is-layout-flex">
<div class="wp-block-button is-style-outline is-style-outline--11"><a class="wp-block-button__link has-text-color" href="https://podcasts.apple.com/us/podcast/stories-for-earth-with-forrest-brown/id1478061144" style="color:#ffffff;" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Apple</a></div>



<div class="wp-block-button is-style-outline is-style-outline--12"><a class="wp-block-button__link has-text-color" href="https://open.spotify.com/show/1p08YiP5SoxJEoFJyeebxR" style="color:#ffffff;" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Spotify</a></div>



<div class="wp-block-button is-style-outline is-style-outline--13"><a class="wp-block-button__link has-text-color" href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCGmH6FisTges9AzQlfbg-hg" style="color:#ffffff;" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">YouTube</a></div>



<div class="wp-block-button is-style-outline is-style-outline--14"><a class="wp-block-button__link has-text-color" href="https://www.stitcher.com/s?fid=463345&amp;refid=stpr" style="color:#ffffff;" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Stitcher</a></div>



<div class="wp-block-button is-style-outline is-style-outline--15"><a class="wp-block-button__link has-text-color" href="https://anchor.fm/s/113fd96c/podcast/rss" style="color:#ffffff;" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">RSS</a></div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div></div>



<hr class="wp-block-separator" />



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="top">Jump to</h2>



<ol class="wp-block-list"><li><a href="#about">About Imbolo Mbue</a></li><li><a href="#transcript">Transcript</a></li><li><a href="#recommendations">Recommendations</a></li></ol>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="about">About the creator</h2>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="750" height="750" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/imbolo-mbue.jpeg?w=300" alt="A headshot of author Imbolo Mbue." class="wp-image-1545" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/imbolo-mbue.jpeg 750w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/08/imbolo-mbue-300x300.jpeg 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/08/imbolo-mbue-150x150.jpeg 150w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 750px) 100vw, 750px" /><figcaption>Source: imbolombue.com/about</figcaption></figure>



<p>Originally from Limbe, Cameroon, Imbolo Mbue is the author of the critically-acclaimed novels <em>Behold the Dreamers</em> and <em>How Beautiful We Were</em>. Her first novel, <em>Behold the Dreamers</em> won the PEN/Faulkner Award for Fiction and was selected for Oprah&#8217;s Book Club. After working on it for years, Mbue&#8217;s second novel, <em>How Beautiful We Were</em>, was published in March 2021. Imbolo Mbue lives in New York.</p>



<p><strong>Official website:</strong> <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.imbolombue.com/" target="_blank">https://www.imbolombue.com/</a><br><strong>Facebook:</strong> <a href="https://www.facebook.com/imbolombue/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">https://www.facebook.com/imbolombue/</a></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="transcript">Transcript</h2>



<p><a href="#top">Back to top ↑</a></p>



<p>I’m Forrest Brown, and you’re listening to <em>Stories for Earth</em>.</p>



<p><em>[music: “Cold Descent” by Forrest Brown]</em></p>



<p>Welcome to Stories for Earth, a podcast about everything climate change in pop culture. I’m excited to finally share the first episode of season 3. It’s crazy to think how fast time has gone. We just recently had our two year anniversary as a podcast, and I’m looking forward to sharing many more interviews and discussions of important stories.</p>



<p>Our first discussion of season 3 is about the novel <em>How Beautiful We Were </em>by Imbolo Mbue, and I am sure that I am probably not pronouncing her name correctly. If you want to support further production of the show, consider becoming a member on Patreon for early access to new episodes. You can also find us on Instagram and Twitter to keep up with the latest news about the show.<br>Let’s cut to the chase. Here’s our discussion of <em>How Beautiful We Were </em>by Imbolo Mbue. I hope you enjoy.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="the-literary-value-of-tragedies">The literary value of tragedies</h2>



<p><a href="#top">Back to top ↑</a></p>



<p>Some stories don’t have happy endings. And I think it’s worth telling you right off the bat that the story I want to talk about today is one of them. This doesn’t make it any less of a good story, a great story, even. We tend to steer clear of stories without happy endings. We’ll listen to a sad story, sure, as long as it ends on a positive note, but something in us makes us hesitant to commit to stories with unhappy endings. I understand this impulse, but at the same time, I think there’s something sad about <em>that</em>, too.</p>



<p>Some of the best stories ever told have unhappy endings. The Ancient Greeks called these tragedies. And just like their opposite, comedies, tragedies offer valuable insights and observations about life and the human condition.</p>



<p class="has-text-align-center" style="font-size:28px;"><strong>Has this info helped you?</strong></p>



<p class="has-text-align-center has-normal-font-size"><em>Stories for Earth is and always will be a free resource to help people imagine brighter futures through the material we discuss. It&#8217;s also created and paid for by one person! Apart from occasional affiliate revenue, donations from people like you is the only way Stories for Earth remains financially feasible.</em></p>



<div class="wp-block-button aligncenter"><a class="wp-block-button__link has-very-light-gray-color has-luminous-vivid-orange-background-color has-text-color has-background" href="https://www.patreon.com/storiesforearth" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Support on Patreon</a></div>



<p></p>



<div class="wp-block-buttons is-content-justification-center is-layout-flex wp-container-core-buttons-is-layout-5 wp-block-buttons-is-layout-flex">
<div class="wp-block-button is-style-fill"><a class="wp-block-button__link has-vivid-cyan-blue-background-color has-background" href="https://venmo.com/code?user_id=3241757261168640196" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Donate on Venmo</a></div>
</div>



<p>Consider one of the older tragedies you might be familiar with: <em>Hamlet </em>by William Shakespeare. <em>Hamlet</em> wrestles with some pretty tough questions—if you haven’t read it before, you’ll know the famous line: “To be, or not to be, that is the question.” This quote has been trivialized to some extent, but it’s actually asking something pretty heavy: is life, for all of its pain and sorrows, actually worth living?</p>



<p>One of my favorite books is also a tragedy. I first read <em>A Farewell to Arms</em> by Ernest Hemingway when I was in high school, and even though it was probably one of the saddest books I’d read at that point, I loved it. It’s even sadder when you learn that many parts of it are based on the author’s real life experiences. I was not the same person after reading that novel.</p>



<p>So all that is to say, <em>How Beautiful We Were </em>is a sad book, but just like some of the best tragedies, it’s not sad for the sake of being sad. It is a brilliant novel, and I think it has a lot to teach us about facing the climate crisis.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="how-beautiful-we-were-plot-summary">&#8220;How Beautiful We Were&#8221; plot summary</h2>



<p><a href="#top">Back to top ↑</a></p>



<p>Set in the fictional village of Kosawa in a fictional African country, <em>How Beautiful We Were </em>is the decades-long story of Kosawa’s fight with the American oil company Pexton. The story begins with news that something in the water is making the village children sick and killing them. We hear heartbreaking accounts of parents burying their sons and daughters with no one left to carry on the family name, and when the villagers seek help from the government, they’re met with gaslighting and denial of any wrongdoing.</p>



<p>Finally, some of the villagers have enough of their children dying, and after kidnapping some of Pexton’s men, things start to escalate. The battle between Pexton and Kosawa rages on for 40 years before reaching any semblance of a resolution, spanning continents and seeing Kosawa fighting in the courts, in the press, in civil demonstrations, and in violent sabotage campaigns to protect their homelands.</p>



<p><strong>Also read:</strong> <a href="https://storiesforearth.com/2020/12/12/weather-by-jenny-offill/">&#8220;Weather&#8221; by Jenny Offill</a></p>



<p>Rather than focusing on one main character, the story takes a collectivist approach, unraveling from the perspective of six members of the Nangi family and from a first person collective perspective of an unknown number of people simply called “The Children.” Each character has a different approach of dealing—or not dealing—with the environmental disaster Pexton caused.</p>



<p>The father, Malabo, ventures to the capital city of Bezam to plead with the government, and his younger brother, Bongo, goes after him. Young Thula studies abroad in the US on a scholarship and returns as a tireless activist. Her mother, Sahel, does her best to raise Thula and her brother while mourning the loss of her husband.</p>



<p>Thula’s little brother Juba, comes back from the dead as a boy and spends the rest of his life struggling with the sensation of being half-dead, half-alive. And Yaya, Juba and Thula’s grandmother, reflects on centuries of destruction and exploitation from foreigners—first through the trans-Atlantic slave trade to rubber plantations to oil fields—and laments what appears to be the end of her home. Finally, The Children grow up in desperation, eventually looking to Thula, their peer, as a leader.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="similarities-between-kosawa-and-cameroon">Similarities between Kosawa and Cameroon</h2>



<p><a href="#top">Back to top ↑</a></p>



<p><em>How Beautiful We Were </em>paints a rich story and explores a number of themes, including imperialism, political corruption, environmental destruction, nonviolent versus violent direct action, and courage in the face of certain defeat. And while we never learn the name of the country where the story takes place, it bears many similarities to Imbolo Mbue’s home country of Cameroon, a relatively small West-Central African country that borders Nigeria to the north and Equatorial Guinea, Gabon, and the Republic of Congo to the south.</p>



<p>Some people refer to Cameroon as “Little Africa” because it encapsulates so many facets of this vast continent. And just like Cameroon, the story of Kosawa is a familiar one in Africa. Africa is an enormous continent, but many of its people have been the victims of violent Western European and American colonizers. The people of Kosawa, too, were often victimized by Western colonizers, such as slave traders, plantation owners, and oil company executives.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="400" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/map-of-cameroon.png?w=800" alt="A picture of Cameroon on a world map." class="wp-image-1556" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/map-of-cameroon.png 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/08/map-of-cameroon-300x150.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/08/map-of-cameroon-768x384.png 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /><figcaption>Source: <a href="https://www.google.com/maps/place/Cameroon/@18.8813013,-28.4145309,3z/data=!4m5!3m4!1s0x10613753703e0f21:0x2b03c44599829b53!8m2!3d5.6487857!4d12.7331543" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Google Maps</a></figcaption></figure>



<p>Returning again to Cameroon, this land was historically inhabited by the Adamawa Emirate in the north and by various chiefdoms and fondoms in the south. That is, until the German Empire imposed brutal colonial rule in the late 1800s. The Germans controlled the colony they called Kamerun—after the Portuguese word for shrimp—until the end of World War I in 1916.</p>



<p>After the war, Cameroon was split in half between the English and the French. It wasn’t until the 1960s that Cameroon gained independence from England and France and reunified as one country. In the many years since, one political party has primarily controlled the country and has focused heavily on oil production to grow its economy. Meanwhile, the country has faced many problems, from political corruption to civil unrest to terrorism. In other words, many of the same problems facing the fictional country from <em>How Beautiful We Were</em>.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="parallels-between-kosawa-and-ecuador">Parallels between Kosawa and Ecuador</h2>



<p><a href="#top">Back to top ↑</a></p>



<p>But in terms of the plot of this novel, I’m reminded of another country, albeit in the Western Hemisphere. Ecuador is a small South American country on the Pacific coast, sharing a border with Peru to the south and Colombia to the north. The Amazon rainforest extends partially into Ecuador, and in the 1960s, the American oil company Texaco, since acquired by Chevron in 2001, started drilling for oil in the Ecuadorian rainforest in what is known as the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lago_Agrio_oil_field" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Lago Agrio oil field</a>. Literally translated: the sour lake oil field.</p>



<p>You probably don’t need me to tell you the effects were disastrous. Texaco didn’t properly dispose of toxic waste from drilling operations—meaning they dumped toxic wastewater into a river that provided drinking water to many indigenous people. Just like the residents of Kosawa in <em>How Beautiful We Were</em>, indigenous people in Ecuador started getting sick and dying. And just like the fictional American oil company Pexton from the novel, the very real oil company called Texaco—now a brand of California-based Chevron—denied any wrongdoing at first, blaming the sickness and death among the indigenous people on <a href="https://www.sfgate.com/green/article/OIL-AND-CANCER-IN-ECUADOR-Ecuadoran-villagers-2557444.php" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">poor sanitation</a>. Which was, of course, a racist lie.</p>



<p>Like the people of Kosawa, Ecuadorians finally had enough of this, and in 1993 some local villagers filed a massive class action lawsuit against Texaco. Seemingly against all odds, the plaintiffs won the class action suit, and in 2011, the <a href="https://sanfrancisco.cbslocal.com/2011/02/14/chevron-fined-9-5-billion-in-ecuador/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Ecuadorian court ordered Chevron to pay $9.5 billion in damages</a>. And sadly, much like the story of <em>How Beautiful We Were</em>, this story is still developing today. Even though Ecuador found Chevron responsible for oil drilling contamination in the Ecuadorian Amazon, Chevron has fought back against the ruling with everything it has.</p>



<p>In 2018, Chevron won a very important appeals case with The Hague in which an <a href="https://www.reuters.com/article/us-chevron-ecuador/international-tribunal-rules-in-favor-of-chevron-in-ecuador-case-idUSKCN1LN1WS" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">international tribunal</a> ruled that the 2011 ruling by Ecuador “…was procured through fraud, bribery and corruption and was based on claims that had been already settled and released by the Republic of Ecuador years earlier.” This effectively rendered the 2011 ruling unenforceable, meaning that in the 25 years that passed since the first class action lawsuit was filed, the indigenous people from the region surrounding Lago Agrio still had not received reparations.</p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="640" height="480" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/640px-texaco_in_ecuador.jpeg?w=640" alt="A photo of oil pollution in the Lago Agrio region in Ecuador." class="wp-image-1559" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/640px-texaco_in_ecuador.jpeg 640w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/08/640px-texaco_in_ecuador-300x225.jpeg 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px" /><figcaption>Oil pollution in the Lago Agrio Oil Field.<br>Source: Photo by Julien Gomba, <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0/" target="_blank">CC BY 2.0</a> via <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://flic.kr/p/4avYH7" target="_blank">Flickr</a> </figcaption></figure>



<p>In fact, three years after the 2018 tribunal ruling, the original plaintiffs <em>still</em> haven’t received reparations. Chevron has spent a lot of money on PR campaigns to push its side of the lawsuit and discredit a key environmental attorney, going so far as to create a publication called <a href="https://theamazonpost.com/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">The Amazon Post</a>, a website that is “…maintained by Chevron to express the company’s views and opinions on a fraudulent lawsuit against the company in Ecuador,” according to the site’s About page. At first glance, The Amazon Post appears to be a legitimate news outlet rather than an aggressive PR initiative from one of the world’s largest oil companies.</p>



<p>And finally, reminiscent of the fates that met Austin, the young journalist from Bézam, and Thula, the quiet-village-girl-turned-fierce-activist, the American lawyer who represented the Ecuadorian villagers in the first class action lawsuit in 1993 has found himself in Chevron’s crosshairs. In August 2020, attorney <a href="https://theintercept.com/2020/01/29/chevron-ecuador-lawsuit-steven-donziger/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Steven Donziger was placed under house arrest</a>. His bank accounts have been frozen, he has been disbarred from practicing law, he’s forbidden from earning money, and he faces exorbitant fines, in addition to other hardships.</p>



<p>I’ll be honest: things don’t look good for Steven Donziger. I hate to use this word after hearing it overused to the point of becoming meaningless since the start of the pandemic, but in many ways, Chevron’s legal campaign against him is unprecedented. According to <em>The Intercept</em>, <a href="https://www.documentcloud.org/documents/6661647-Demonize-Donziger.html" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Chevron has flat-out said</a> its strategy in overturning the Ecuador court ruling is to demonize Steven Donziger.</p>



<p><strong>Also read:</strong> <a href="https://storiesforearth.com/2020/08/04/joy-harjo-crazy-brave-an-american-sunrise/">Joy Harjo: &#8220;Crazy Brave,&#8221; &#8220;An American Sunrise,&#8221; And The Land</a></p>



<p>As you can tell, this is an extremely complicated legal case that will likely be studied by law students for years to come. If you’re interested in learning more about the latest developments regarding Chevron, Ecuador, and Steven Donziger, I recommend listening to season five of the excellent podcast <em>Drilled</em> from journalist Amy Westervelt. I’ll include a link in the show notes.</p>



<p>So what’s the takeaway from all of this? Well, Kosawa might be a fictional African village suffering the consequences of a corrupt government that opened its doors wide to an irresponsible oil company, but it sadly bears a strong resemblance to countries like Ecuador who are now dealing with some very similar problems in real life.</p>



<p>And just like the battles against the fictional company Pexton from <em>How Beautiful We Were</em>, the court cases involving Chevron and Ecuador just go to show how far the fossil fuel industry will go to protect its interests.</p>



<p>As the latest IPCC report makes abundantly clear, there is no scenario in which the fossil fuel industry continues to exist if we’re to have a livable planet. But how we take down the fossil fuel industry is the biggest question that remains unanswered.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="violent-versus-nonviolent-direct-action">Violent versus nonviolent direct action</h2>



<p><a href="#top">Back to top ↑</a></p>



<p>As <em>How Beautiful We Were</em> starts to pick up steam, a clear dichotomy begins to emerge in how different villagers of Kosawa fight back against Pexton. We see this first when Malabo and his friends kidnap the men from Pexton, but this theme becomes more fleshed out after Thula leaves the village to attend university in the United States.</p>



<p>After arriving in New York City, Thula reconnects with Austin, the journalist from Bezam who originally broke the story about Pexton’s misdeeds. Austin starts taking Thula to meetings with activists who work on various human rights issues, and it doesn’t take long before Thula becomes a fierce activist herself. But unlike some of the other villagers taking a stand against Pexton, Thula is staunchly committed to non-violent direct action.</p>



<p>The first-person collective narrator known simply as The Children has a different approach, though. These people are Thula’s peers, and they exchange letters back and forth with her about what should be done to stop Pexton. Thula forbids them from using violence, threatening to withhold funding for their cause if they violate their agreement to remain peaceful. But after a certain point, The Children use funds from Thula to buy guns from a corrupt soldier anyway, using them to murder a number of different Pexton employees.</p>



<p>The Children also carry out sabotage campaigns, setting fire to Pexton facilities in the hopes that they will finally leave after seeing how unwelcome they are. Meanwhile, Thula eventually returns to Africa, becoming a school teacher and organizing massive nationwide protests against the corrupt government that lets Pexton destroy the environment and make the people sick. Thula works her entire adult life trying to enact change through peaceful protest, but in the end, she’s largely unsuccessful.</p>



<p><strong>Also read:</strong> <a href="https://storiesforearth.com/2020/01/14/ishmael-daniel-quinn-climate-change/">“Ishmael” by Daniel Quinn, Climate Change, and Moving Beyond a Vision of&nbsp;Doom</a></p>



<p>In fact, the character who seems to be the most well-off by the end is Juba, Thula’s younger brother who came back from the dead as a child after getting very sick from Pexton’s poison. As an adult, Juba can’t shake the feeling that he never fully returned to the realm of the living, constantly feeling as though he’s half-dead, half-alive.</p>



<p>I read this as a metaphor for how Juba chooses to engage with the war between Kosawa and Pexton. Juba isn’t violent, but he also doesn’t have the same activist’s passion that we see in his sister. Instead, Juba goes to the best schools in the country and gets a government job doing the bidding of corrupt officials and politicians. He marries a woman named Nubia, named after one of the earliest civilizations in ancient Africa, who has somewhat of a scammer’s philosophy. She hates the corrupt government as much as anyone else, but instead of fighting it at great personal cost, she prefers to take advantage of the crooked system to benefit herself as much as possible.</p>



<p>Near the end of the book, we see Juba and Nubia living a life of luxury while Thula lives a modest lifestyle as an activist school teacher. Speaking about Thula on page 343, The Children say, “One angry woman did everything, and she failed.” The book ends with a judge forcing the residents of Kosawa to relocate. The judge doesn’t deny the damage Pexton has caused, but he also doesn’t think the law can hold them accountable. Given the extent of the damage, it’s best for the villagers to just find a new home.</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="the-best-way-forward">The best way forward?</h2>



<p><a href="#top">Back to top ↑</a></p>



<p>After reading <em>How Beautiful We Were</em> and reflecting on the world we currently live in, one that is honestly so much more bleak and dystopian than the one in this novel, I’m not sure of how we should proceed.</p>



<p>High profile climate organizations like Extinction Rebellion and the Sunrise Movement are committed to peaceful direct action, but how long can this continue to be a viable strategy? At what point do some people renege on this principle and resort to violence? Many important movements throughout history have been fought with violence. Is that what the environmental movement will one day be forced to do?</p>



<p>But honestly, out of the three responses I see in <em>How Beautiful We Were</em>, I think Juba’s response might be the most relatable to many people. Heartbroken and half-dead, many of us walk through life like zombies, complying with our evil capitalist overlords while we scheme to exploit the broken system to our advantage. Jia Tolentino makes many excellent observations about this phenomenon in her essay “<a href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/p07sqc95" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">The Story of a Generation in Seven Scams</a>” from her essay collection <em>Trick Mirror. </em>Many of us know the system is fucked, but what can we do about it? At a time when <a href="https://jacobinmag.com/2020/10/united-states-class-based-wealth-distribution" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">one percent of the world’s population owns the vast majority of the world’s wealth</a>, playing the system to our advantage is what’s expected of us. It’s a vicious cycle until some external force breaks that cycle, or the house of cards comes crashing down under its own weight.</p>



<p>I’m sure we’ll see a combination of all three responses, as the environmental movement progresses and our insane society continues to flirt even more with the threat of apocalypse. I strongly believe there is no one right way to tackle this enormous problem. Perhaps a hybrid approach will be the path we take. As for me, I don’t want to see violence and bloodshed erupt as we struggle to save our planet. But I have to wonder: are there limits to peaceful protest, and what will happen if we cross that threshold?</p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="outro">Outro</h2>



<p><a href="#top">Back to top ↑</a></p>



<p>Stories for Earth is created by me, Forrest Brown. The music you heard in this episode is also by me. If you want to support further production of the show, consider becoming a member on Patreon. For just a couple bucks a month, you’ll get early access to each new episode, and you’ll help me keep making Stories for Earth.</p>



<p>Thanks for listening, and I hope you’ll join us for season 3, episode 2 for our discussion on the 2004 film <em>The Day After Tomorrow.</em></p>



<h2 class="wp-block-heading" id="recommendations">Recommendations</h2>



<p><a href="#top">Back to top ↑</a></p>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="259" height="400" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/behold-the-dreamers-by-imbolo-mbue.jpeg?w=194" alt="Book cover for Behold the Dreamers by Imbolo Mbue." class="wp-image-1561" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/behold-the-dreamers-by-imbolo-mbue.jpeg 259w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/08/behold-the-dreamers-by-imbolo-mbue-194x300.jpeg 194w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 259px) 100vw, 259px" /></figure>



<p><strong>Book:</strong> <em>Behold the Dreamers</em> by Imbolo Mbue</p>



<p>→ <a href="https://bookshop.org/a/140/9780525509714" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Buy <strong>NEW</strong> on Bookshop from $15.64</a> (affiliate)<br>→ <a href="http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/1023125245">Find at your local library</a></p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator" />



<figure class="wp-block-image size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="267" height="400" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/the-shock-doctrine-by-naomi-klein.jpeg?w=200" alt="Book cover for The Shock Doctrine by Naomi Klein." class="wp-image-1563" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/the-shock-doctrine-by-naomi-klein.jpeg 267w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/08/the-shock-doctrine-by-naomi-klein-200x300.jpeg 200w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 267px) 100vw, 267px" /></figure>



<p><strong>Book:</strong> <em>The Shock Doctrine: The Rise of Disaster Capitalism</em> by Naomi Klein</p>



<p> → <a href="https://bookshop.org/a/140/9780312427993" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Buy <strong>NEW</strong> on Bookshop from $20.24</a> (affiliate)<br>→ <a href="http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/1003865219" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Find at your local library</a></p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator" />



<figure class="wp-block-image size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="800" height="400" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/steven-donziger-the-intercept.png?w=300" alt="A photo of lawyer Steven Donziger." class="wp-image-1566" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/steven-donziger-the-intercept.png 800w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/08/steven-donziger-the-intercept-300x150.png 300w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/08/steven-donziger-the-intercept-768x384.png 768w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 800px) 100vw, 800px" /><figcaption>Source: Photo by Annie Tritt for The Intercept via <a href="https://theintercept.imgix.net/wp-uploads/sites/1/2020/01/01152020_intercept_steven-Donziger-2126-1580226145-e1580226220277.jpg?auto=compress%2Cformat&amp;q=90&amp;fit=crop&amp;w=2000&amp;h=1000" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">The Intercept</a></figcaption></figure>



<p><strong>Article:</strong> &#8220;How The Environmental Lawyer Who Won A Massive Judgment Against Chevron Lost Everything&#8221; by Sharon Lerner in <em>The Intercept</em></p>



<p>→ <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://theintercept.com/2020/01/29/chevron-ecuador-lawsuit-steven-donziger/" target="_blank">Read the articl</a><a href="https://theintercept.com/2020/01/29/chevron-ecuador-lawsuit-steven-donziger/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">e</a></p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator" />



<figure class="wp-block-image size-medium"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="488" height="729" src="/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/crude-documentary.png?w=201" alt="The official movie poster for Crude: The Real Price of Oil." class="wp-image-1569" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2021/08/crude-documentary.png 488w, /wp-content/uploads/2021/08/crude-documentary-201x300.png 201w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 488px) 100vw, 488px" /><figcaption>Source: <a href="https://www.imdb.com/title/tt1326204/mediaviewer/rm1125746688/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">IMDB</a></figcaption></figure>



<p><strong>Documentary:</strong> <em>Crude: The Real Price of Oil</em> from Joe Berlinger</p>



<p>→ <a href="https://youtu.be/BvrZRvgwBS8" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Watch on YouTube</a><br>→ <a rel="noreferrer noopener" href="https://www.amazon.com/gp/video/detail/B017UOJ1CQ/ref=atv_dp_share_cu_r" target="_blank">Watch on Prime Video</a></p>



<div class="wp-block-group alignfull"><div class="wp-block-group__inner-container is-layout-flow wp-block-group-is-layout-flow">
<div class="wp-block-coblocks-hero alignfull coblocks-hero-82610395659"><div class="wp-block-coblocks-hero__inner has-background hero-center-left-align has-padding has-huge-padding has-left-content" style="background-color:#f3f3f3;min-height:500px;"><div class="wp-block-coblocks-hero__content-wrapper"><div class="wp-block-coblocks-hero__content" style="max-width:560px;">
<h2 class="wp-block-heading">Like what you see? Become a Patreon member today for as little as $1 a month.</h2>



<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><a href="https://www.patreon.com/storiesforearth" target="_blank"><img loading="lazy" decoding="async" width="434" height="102" src="/wp-content/uploads/2020/12/become_a_patron_button402x.png?w=434" alt="" class="wp-image-1007" srcset="/wp-content/uploads/2020/12/become_a_patron_button402x.png 434w, /wp-content/uploads/2020/12/become_a_patron_button402x-300x71.png 300w" sizes="auto, (max-width: 434px) 100vw, 434px" /></a></figure>
</div></div></div></div>
</div></div>



<p></p>
<p>The post <a href="/2021/08/24/how-beautiful-we-were-imbolo-mbue/">&#8220;How Beautiful We Were&#8221; by Imbolo Mbue: Summary &amp; Analysis</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Stories for Earth</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Coming Soon: Stories for Earth Season 3</title>
		<link>/2021/08/10/coming-soon-season-3/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Forrest Brown]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 10 Aug 2021 16:59:58 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Episodes]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[books]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[climate change]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[season 3]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[trailer]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://storiesforearth.com/?p=1535</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Season 3 of Stories for Earth is coming soon to Apple Podcasts, Spotify, Sticher, or wherever you get podcasts. Subscribe for updates on new episodes!</p>
<p>The post <a href="/2021/08/10/coming-soon-season-3/">Coming Soon: Stories for Earth Season 3</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Stories for Earth</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p><em>Stories for Earth relies on contributions from our listeners and readers to produce high quality, in-depth content. If you buy something using the links on our website, we may</em> <em>earn a small commission, at no extra cost to you. <em>For more information</em>, see our <a href="https://storiesforearth.com/affiliate-disclosure/">Affiliate Disclosure</a>.</em></p>



<hr class="wp-block-separator" />



<figure class="wp-block-embed is-type-rich is-provider-spotify wp-block-embed-spotify wp-embed-aspect-21-9 wp-has-aspect-ratio"><div class="wp-block-embed__wrapper">
<div class="embed-spotify"><iframe title="Spotify Embed: Coming Soon: Stories for Earth Season 3" style="border-radius: 12px" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/episode/7jHANwxSpCmXBh6mLDIDSf?si=HutNdUm-TACve1tCTPW9RQ&#038;dl_branch=1&#038;utm_source=oembed"></iframe></div>
</div></figure>



<p>This is a podcast about the greatest story ever told. It’s actually a story that’s <em>being</em> told because we are all living through it right now, and we will be for the rest of our lives. I’m talking, of course, about the climate emergency.</p>



<p>But the tricky thing about stories unfolding in real time is that we can’t see the whole picture yet. Remember, we’re all characters in this story, and none of us have a narrator’s God’s-eye-view of what this all means or what happens next. So what do we do? We tell stories ourselves to make sense of this muddled reality. We write novels. We program video games. We direct films. We sing songs.</p>



<p>We have so many ways of telling stories, and I believe that paying attention to some of the best ones can help us as we try to navigate the bigger story, the climate story, in our own lives. We’ve already talked about some incredible stories on the show. Last season, we started out by talking about one of the greatest video games ever made, <a href="https://storiesforearth.com/2020/06/09/final-fantasy-vii-environmentalism/">Final Fantasy VII</a>, a tale of an ecoterrorist organization that must persevere against all odds in the fight to save the planet.</p>



<p>The current <a href="https://storiesforearth.com/2020/08/04/joy-harjo-crazy-brave-an-american-sunrise/">US Poet Laureate Joy Harjo</a> spoke to us through poetry about what it was like when her people could hear the songs of plants, and why it’s imperative that all of us learn how to hear them now. A <a href="https://storiesforearth.com/2020/09/22/okja-bong-joon-ho/">farm girl from South Korea</a> showed just how far people will go to save the ones they love and how creating the world we want might just start with how we engage with capitalism.</p>



<p>In her novel <em><a href="https://storiesforearth.com/2020/12/12/weather-by-jenny-offill/">Weather</a></em>, Jenny Offill taught us how a New York City librarian narrowly avoided becoming a doomer by learning to always look for the obligatory note of hope. A <a href="https://storiesforearth.com/2021/01/26/infest-the-rats-nest-by-king-gizzard-the-lizard-wizard/">heavy metal band from Australia</a> painted a vivid and terrifying audio picture of what kind of future we might expect if we don’t drastically change course immediately.</p>



<p>My friend from across the Atlantic and I had a makeshift therapy session with each other to process the eon-level view of life on this planet from <a href="https://storiesforearth.com/2021/02/23/the-overstory-richard-powers/"><em>The Overstory</em> by Richard Powers</a>, and <a href="https://storiesforearth.com/2021/04/15/gun-island-the-great-derangement-amitav-ghosh/">Amitav Ghosh</a>, one of the most eminent writers on literature and the climate crisis, took us on a journey through the history of world literature to show us how modern literature is failing to address climate change and what must be done to change that.</p>



<p>This August, we’ll embark on another journey through stories in all forms to discover what they can teach us about living in an age verging on climate chaos. We’ll see how those least responsible for climate change suffer the worst consequences through heartbreaking novels like <a href="https://bookshop.org/a/140/9780593132425" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener"><em>How Beautiful We Were </em>by Imbolo Mbue</a>.</p>



<p>We’ll consider the story of a lone robot left to clean up the mess humans left on Earth while they rocket through space in search of a new planet to inhabit. We’ll find inspiration from a brave young princess in an imaginary world as she struggles to simultaneously prevent a war and save the planet. And we might just revisit one of the first major Hollywood films ever made about climate change.</p>



<p>It’s going to be a powerful exploration into the different stories that can help us better understand the real-life story of climate change, and I hope you’ll tag along. Our first stop is coming up shortly through a discussion on <em>How Beautiful We Were </em>by Imbolo Mbue. Thank you for listening, and I look forward to seeing you then for the first episode of Stories for Earth Season 3.</p>



<div class="wp-block-cover alignfull has-background-dim has-background-gradient" style="background:linear-gradient(135deg,rgb(92,145,60) 0%,rgb(169,209,153) 100%);min-height:350px;aspect-ratio:unset;"><div class="wp-block-cover__inner-container is-layout-flow wp-block-cover-is-layout-flow">
<div class="wp-block-jetpack-layout-grid alignfull column1-desktop-grid__span-10 column1-desktop-grid__start-2 column1-desktop-grid__row-1 column1-tablet-grid__span-8 column1-tablet-grid__row-1 column1-mobile-grid__span-4 column1-mobile-grid__row-1 wp-block-jetpack-layout-gutter__medium">
<div class="wp-block-jetpack-layout-grid-column wp-block-jetpack-layout-grid__padding-none">
<h3 class="has-text-color wp-block-heading" style="color:#ffffff;font-size:clamp(30.693px, 1.918rem + ((1vw - 3.2px) * 2.285), 54px);px;">Never miss an episode</h3>



<p class="margin-bottom-half has-text-color" style="color:#ffffff;font-size:clamp(14px, 0.875rem + ((1vw - 3.2px) * 0.392), 18px);px;">Subscribe wherever you enjoy podcasts:</p>



<div class="wp-block-buttons margin-top-none is-layout-flex wp-block-buttons-is-layout-flex">
<div class="wp-block-button is-style-outline is-style-outline--16"><a class="wp-block-button__link has-text-color" href="https://podcasts.apple.com/us/podcast/stories-for-earth-with-forrest-brown/id1478061144" style="color:#ffffff;" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Apple</a></div>



<div class="wp-block-button is-style-outline is-style-outline--17"><a class="wp-block-button__link has-text-color" href="https://open.spotify.com/show/1p08YiP5SoxJEoFJyeebxR" style="color:#ffffff;" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Spotify</a></div>



<div class="wp-block-button is-style-outline is-style-outline--18"><a class="wp-block-button__link has-text-color" href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCGmH6FisTges9AzQlfbg-hg" style="color:#ffffff;" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">YouTube</a></div>



<div class="wp-block-button is-style-outline is-style-outline--19"><a class="wp-block-button__link has-text-color" href="https://www.stitcher.com/s?fid=463345&amp;refid=stpr" style="color:#ffffff;" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">Stitcher</a></div>



<div class="wp-block-button is-style-outline is-style-outline--20"><a class="wp-block-button__link has-text-color" href="https://anchor.fm/s/113fd96c/podcast/rss" style="color:#ffffff;" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">RSS</a></div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div></div>
<p>The post <a href="/2021/08/10/coming-soon-season-3/">Coming Soon: Stories for Earth Season 3</a> appeared first on <a href="/">Stories for Earth</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
